<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another sermon preached to the Honorable House of Commons now assembled in Parliament, November the fifth, 1641 by Cornelius Burges, D.D. ; wherein, among other things, are shewed a list of some of the popish traytors in England.</title>
            <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12682988</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12682988</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65693</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65693)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 681:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Another sermon preached to the Honorable House of Commons now assembled in Parliament, November the fifth, 1641 by Cornelius Burges, D.D. ; wherein, among other things, are shewed a list of some of the popish traytors in England.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 65 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.B. for P. Stephens and C. Meridith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 65.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65693:1"/>
            <p>ANOTHER SERMON Preached to the <hi>Honorable Houſe of Commons</hi> now aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, <hi>November the fifth,</hi> 1641.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> CORNELIUS BURGES. <hi>D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein, among other things, are ſhewed</hi> A Liſt of ſome of the <hi>Popiſh Traytors</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That their <hi>Treaſons</hi> were not <hi>occaſioned</hi> by our Laws, but from <hi>Principles</hi> of their owne <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That their <hi>Prieſts</hi> are bound to infuſe <hi>ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Principles</hi> into them.</p>
            <p>The courſes taken by their <hi>Preiſts and Ieſuites</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate them unto <hi>Treaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Experimentall <hi>Prognostication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. B.</hi> for <hi>P. Stephens</hi> and <hi>C. Meridith,</hi> at the <hi>Gilded Lion,</hi> and at the <hi>Craine in S. Pauls Church-Yard,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65693:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65693:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> now aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen firſt I underſtood that You had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned only my ſelfe to preach unto You at that Great and happy <hi>Solemnity</hi> upon the <hi>Fifth</hi> of <hi>November</hi> laſt, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged my Proviſion, becauſe there was no other to ſecond me in that Service.</p>
            <p>But when I came to ſet before You what the Lord had brought to my hand,<note place="margin">The Tumults in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> I found You ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver laid with buſineſſe of ſuch high importance as would hardly permit You to hear any ſermon at all. This conſtrained me to contract the two firſt Parts of my Sermon, and wholly to ſuppreſſe the third; except the laſt branch of the laſt <hi>Vſe,</hi> which I found meanes to affix to my ſecond Point.</p>
            <p>It was far from my thoughts, and above my hopes, that ſuch a mangled Peice ſhould gaine ſuch Acceptance with You, as to be held worthy of Your <hi>Thankes,</hi> or of <hi>Publique View.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſeeing Your pleaſure is, to <hi>Order</hi> the <hi>Publiſhing</hi> it, I obey. Only I have now added the remainder
<pb facs="tcp:65693:3"/> of that Proviſion, with which I could not at firſt preſent You, by reaſon of thoſe Indiſpenſable Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions then preſſing on You.</p>
            <p>The Lord of Heaven direct all Your ways, make them plaine before You, proſper You in them, and hold all Your hearts firme to Himſelfe and in Vnity among Your ſelves; ſet You more effectually upon, and carry You more ſtrongly through that moſt neceſſary (and of all other moſt Important) Work, even the <hi>Perfecting</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi> of this <hi>Church</hi> (by the aſſiſtance of a free Nationall Synod, if Your wiſdomes ſhould ſo thinke meet) for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecuring of our <hi>Religion</hi> from Corruption in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> from Pollution in <hi>Worſhip,</hi> from ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> from Exorbitancy and Tyranny in <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Government and Diſcipline,</hi> and from <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> (under a falſe guiſe of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty</hi>) which is farre worſe than Tyranny.</p>
            <p>Hee alſo make You all more zealous to ſettle a <hi>Ministery</hi> worthy of the Glorious Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in every Congregation, and a ſufficient maintainance for all faithfull Labourers therein. He raiſe You higher and higher in honour with God and Man, and carry You ſtil in his Boſome till hee hath brought You to Glory. All of which, is, and ſhall be the inceſſant prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble ſervant C. BURGES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65693:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 76.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Surely the rage of man ſhall praiſe thee, the reſt of the rage ſhalt thou reſtraine.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text and this day doe well agree.<note place="margin">Introduction ſhewing. I. The <hi>fitneſſe.</hi>
               </note> Never did day more exactly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the truth of this Text. Never did Text more fully ſet forth the Workes of this Day, whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <hi>the rage of man,</hi> or the <hi>Power of God</hi> in over-ruling thereof to his own <hi>Praiſe</hi> and our preſervation.</p>
            <p>This is that day wherein the moſt prodigious <hi>rage of man,</hi> that ever the Sun beheld, or that Hell it ſelfe boyled up to an height juſtly execrable to all the world, was ready to break forth out of the nethermoſt Pit, againſt our Late King, Queene, the Royall Seed, the Parliament, Church, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, this Place, our ſelves, and all ours, all at once. And this is that day wherein our God came riding to us in his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of Triumph, and made himſelfe <hi>fearfull in prayſes,</hi> by <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders,</hi> and leaving us no more to doe, but to <hi>praiſe</hi> his Name, and lengthening out our happineſſe joyfully to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate this Publike Anniverſarie of that ſtupendious Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>So that,<note place="margin">II. The <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </note> while Interpreters contend and ſweat about the ſpeciall occaſion of this Gratulatory Song, whether penned as a Laſting Trophee of the many Victories atchieved by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> over the <hi>Philiſtines, Moabites, Syrians,</hi> and others (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.) or of the diſcomfiture of that formidable Army of the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Aſa</hi> (2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 20.) Or of the ſelfe-deſtroying of that huge Hoſt of <hi>the children of Ammon, Moab, and mount Seir,</hi> in the reign of <hi>Jehoſhaphat.</hi> 2 <hi>Ch.</hi> 20. Or rather, (which is more probable) as a Pillar of Gratitude in the time of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> for the wonderfull defeat of thoſe numberleſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65693:4"/> Forces of blaſphemous <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> nigh to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where an Angel went forth, and in one night, and ſlew 185000. men, in the campe of the <hi>Aſſyrians, King.</hi> 19. Sure we are,<note place="margin">Introduction.</note> that none of all thoſe Great Acts of the Lord, ever ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred greater occaſion to advance a Publike Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, beyond the faint and dull ſtraine of Proſe, to the ſprite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courage of a Verſe, by the gratefull violence of a Poetick Rapture, truly divine, than that admirable, and even inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable over powering of the matchleſſe fury of thoſe <hi>Romiſh</hi> Pioneers, imployed in that Maſter-peece of Helliſh Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon,</hi> affords unto us, and all Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of greateſt exilience, and of utmoſt induſtry to <hi>make His Praiſe glorious,</hi> who juſtly <hi>inhabiteth the praiſes of Iſrael,</hi> and is (in himſelfe) <hi>exalted above all bleſſing and Praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, on this Day if ever, and even <hi>here</hi> alſo, if any where, <hi>brake He the arrows of the bow, the ſhield, the ſword, and battell,</hi> whereby he is become <hi>more glorious and excellent than the mountaines of prey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, <hi>the stout-hearted are spoiled, they have ſtept their ſleep, and none of the men of might</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In that great ſlaughter in the hoſt of <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi> the <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Captaines,</hi> and <hi>mighty men of Valour,</hi> were all cut off 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.21.</note> 
               <hi>have found their hands. At thy rebuke, O God of Jacob, both the Chariot, and the horſe are caſt into a dead ſleep. — Thou didst cauſe judgement to be heard from heaven; the earth feared, and was ſtill, when God aroſe to judgement, to ſave all the meek of the earth.</hi> Therefore wee, even wee alſo will for ever ſay, and ſing to thy Name, as thy people of old,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surely, the rage of man ſhall praiſe thee, the reſt of the rage ſhalt thou reſtraine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">III. The <hi>Summe.</hi>
               </note>Which words (<hi>Janus</hi> like) have a double Aſpect. For, they looke not only backwards, as a Thankfull Remembrance of what God hath already done; but alſo forwards, as a Prophetick Reſolution, and well grounded Concluſion of Faith, touching the conſtant ordering and curbing <hi>the rage</hi> of all his and our enemies, ſo as to get himſelfe glory out of all, to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">IV. The Parts of the <hi>Text.</hi>
               </note>If we make a Diſtribution of the Text, there will be found in it an <hi>Aſſeveration,</hi> and an <hi>Aſſertion.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65693:4"/>
               <item>1. An <hi>Aſſeveration,</hi> in the firſt word, <hi>ſurely.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> conſiſting of two ſimple <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> diverſifyed by the various conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>ſubject</hi> of them both, <hi>the rage of man;</hi> which if we conſider,
<list>
                     <item>1. As the permiſſion of it, by his wiſe and powerfull ordering, may conduce to his honour; So, <hi>the rage of man ſhall praiſe thee.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. As the breaking out of it further might prove inconſiſtent with his Glory; So, <hi>the reſt of the rage ſhalt thou reſtraine.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The time allotted me will not be ſufficient for a diſtinct proſecution of every Obſervation which theſe ſeverall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches afford. And your weightie Affaires preſſe for all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. I ſhall therefore fixe only upon the principall points in the ſhorteſt way, after a briefe explication of the words of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Explication. <hi>Surely,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>] So I find the Originall <hi>[Chi]</hi> rendred by our Engliſh Tranſlators, Old &amp; New, and by ſome of the Latine, correſpondent thereunto. I acknowledge the Hebrew word to be moſt frequently uſed as a Cauſall particle [<hi>For,</hi> or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe.</hi>] Howbeit it is, not ſeldome, put for a vehement <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration,</hi> or Atteſtation, and tranſlated, <hi>Surely,</hi> or <hi>Verily.</hi> Thus, <hi>Iacob</hi> to <hi>Laban;</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 31.42.</note> 
               <hi>Surely, thou hadſt ſent me away em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty.</hi> So <hi>Judah to Jacob;</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.10.</note> 
               <hi>Except we had lingered, ſurely we had returned a ſecond time.</hi> And, <hi>ſurely there is no inchantment againſt Jacob,</hi> ſaid wretched <hi>Balaam</hi> of bleſſed <hi>Iſrael.</hi> In all which places, and many moe, the Originall word is the ſame that is in this Text.</p>
            <p>This may be ſufficient warrant for our Tranſlation, which is both pertinent, and emphaticall. <hi>Pertinent,</hi> becauſe, had the word been otherwiſe rendred, the ſenſe had been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured; for that it is not a Reaſon of the Premiſſes, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65693:5"/> a Concluſion deduced from them. <hi>Emphaticall</hi> alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it lively expreſſeth the aſſurance of Faith in Gods Wiſedome, Power, and Goodneſſe for the happy diſpoſing of that Rage, which he ſhall at any time pleaſe to permit, and for the maſtering and ſuppreſſing of the <hi>reſidue,</hi> which hee ſhall finde cauſe to <hi>reſtraine.</hi> You ſee the <hi>Aſſeveration.</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Aſſertion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The rage, <hi>from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ex a deſcere.</note>
               <hi>The rage.]</hi> So I tranſlate <hi>[Chamath.]</hi> not <hi>anger;</hi> as ſome; not yet <hi>wrath,</hi> as others. <hi>Anger</hi> is too milde, <hi>wrath,</hi> too ſhort to expreſſe it by. I know <hi>anger, wrath, and rage,</hi> (or <hi>fury</hi>) be ſometimes promiſcuouſly put one for another. But withall, I finde them ſometimes<note n="*" place="margin">Anger is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and wrath is raging. <hi>So the old Tranſlation. <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.4.</hi>
               </note> diſtinguiſhed, and in ſtrictneſſe ſome difference may bee found betweene them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anger</hi> is the boyling of the blood about the heart, cauſing a commotion of the ſpirits that are neere. <hi>Wrath</hi> is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of that inward diſtemper by lookes, geſtures, or actions tending to revenge. But <hi>Rage</hi> is the extremitie of both the former, cauſing the <hi>heart to ſtudy deſtruction</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.2.</note>, to meditate and contrive the utmoſt of miſchiefe and villanie; and, the outward man to watch, and lay hold upon all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities and occaſions of putting it in execution, out of the depth of malice, and in the height of fury. Beſides, it is of longer continuance than <hi>anger,</hi> ſtrictly ſo called. It is ſuch an inveterate anger as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>resteth in the boſome of fooles,</hi> keepes houſe, and conſtant reſidence there; being deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted, and wrought up unto a ſetled habite, which (though it doth not alwayes actually breake forth, yet) is continually deſirous of vent, like fire impatient of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint.</p>
            <p>That all this is compriſed under the word here uſed, is manifeſt both by the judgement of the Learned, who have expounded it, and by the uſe of it in Sacred Writt. Therefore ſome expreſſe it by <hi>Fervor: Tremellius</hi> by <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> or a burning heate like to that of an Oven, or Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, which ſets the whole man in a flame, that cannot, without extraordinary meanes, bee quenched, or allayed. And the Scriptures informe us both of a <hi>rage</hi> within <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65693:5"/> 2.1. <hi>Why doe the heathen rage,</hi> which is immediately expounded by an internall act, the <hi>imagining</hi> (or <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating) of a vaine thing:</hi> and, of a <hi>rage</hi> without too, namely, the <hi>rage of the tongue.</hi> Hoſea 7 16. and the <hi>rage</hi> of the <hi>hand. Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath</hi> (or <hi>rage) for it was cruell,</hi> ſaid dying <hi>Jacob,</hi> touching the bloody butchery committed by his two Sonnes, <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> upon the newly circumciſed <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites,</hi> in cold blood. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 49.7. Which alſo ſhewes the ſetled permanencie, and predominancie of ſuch a Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in a wicked man.</p>
            <p>This <hi>rage</hi> is amplified by the ſubject wherein it is, <hi>Man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of man. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For it is called, the rage <hi>of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> The Text names no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall, whether <hi>Sennacherib</hi> (of whoſe <hi>rage</hi> God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe took notice,<note n="e" place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.27.</note>) or any other blaſtering Tyrant, or boyſterous <hi>Ajax;</hi> but indefinitely termes it <hi>[Chamath Adam] the rage of man,</hi> a Livery that fits the ſhoulders of any wicked man in the world.</p>
            <p>And this indefinite expreſſion is uſed partly for <hi>diſcovery,</hi> and partly out of <hi>contempt</hi> of the <hi>man</hi> that is here demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> to point out the vicious quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and corrupt eſtate of the <hi>man,</hi> in whom this <hi>rage</hi> reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. It is the rage of <hi>Adam,</hi> of the <hi>old man,</hi> of every man that hath not put off the <hi>first Adam,</hi> and is not ingraffed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>ſecond.</hi> Therefore is it called the <hi>rage of man;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>of every man</hi> yet remaining upon the old Stock, or <hi>the firſt man, which is of the earth, earthly</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note>. Hence is he called, <hi>a man of the earth. Pſalm.</hi> 10.18 <hi>the violent man. Pſalm.</hi> 18.48. <hi>the bloody and deceitfull man. Pſal.</hi> 55.23. and by ſuch like Epithites.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By way of <hi>contempt,</hi> to ſhew that, be the <hi>rage</hi> what it will, it is yet but the rage of a weake ſilly <hi>man,</hi> that is of baſe originall, and of too ſmall a ſtrength to grapple with Omnipotencie. Thus, in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 9.19. <hi>Ariſe, O Lord, let not Man prevaile.</hi> Where the Strong GOD is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to impotent <hi>Man.</hi> So the next words. <hi>Put them in fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, O Lord, that the Nations may know themſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65693:6"/> to be but men:</hi> that is, poore weake graſhoppers,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe houſes are clay, whoſe foundation is in the duſt, that are cruſhed before the moth:</hi> ſo that neither<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>can their hearts endure, nor their hands be ſtrong in the dayes that God ſhall deale with them Wilt thou yet ſay before him that ſlayeth thee, I am God? But thou ſhalt be a man, and no God, in the hand of him that ſlayeth thee. Ezek</hi> 28.9. This is the <hi>man;</hi> and this, the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> which God makes of him in whom this <hi>rage</hi> is found. But againſt whom is it bent? If we conſult the ſtory, wee ſhall find God complaining that it went very high, for it reached even unto Himſelfe.<note place="margin">Explication.</note> 
               <hi>I know thy abode, — and thy rage againſt mee,</hi> ſaith the Lord. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19, 27. that is, firſt more immediately, by blaſphemous <hi>speaking againſt the God of Hieruſalem, as againſt the Gods of the people of the earth,</hi> which were,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>the worke of the hands of man.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.19. Secondly, mediately, through the Loines of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and ſuch of his people as truſted in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now, what of all this <hi>rage of man</hi> againſt God and his ſervants? The Text tells you what is predicated of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Shall praiſe thee. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>It <hi>ſhall praiſe thee.</hi>] Or, as the old Tranſlation hath it, it <hi>ſhall turne to thy praiſe.</hi> Praiſe is nothing elſe but the exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Excellency, whereby it may be had in reverence and honour. This is that which redounds unto God from <hi>the rage of man:</hi> not intentionally on mans part, as if he in his <hi>rage</hi> aymed at it: for ſo, <hi>God is not in all his thoughts. Pſal.</hi> 10.4. But occaſionally on <hi>mans</hi> part, and efficaciouſly on Gods, who brings light out of darkneſſe, and good out of evill. His Power and Providence ſo ordereth and diſpoſeth all the malicious machinations, and bloody deſignes of the moſt deſperate men, that they goe away with the ſhame, his people with joy, and himſelfe with the honour. And this he doth not onely by maſtering them in their greateſt rage, and compelling them to acknowledge his power, but alſo by giving ſuch iſſue thereunto, as ſhall produce effects quite contrary to thoſe which they intended. Thus, the <hi>rage</hi> of <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren, in ſelling him to the <hi>Iſhmaelites</hi> turned to Gods praiſe, <hi>As for you,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ioſeph, Yee thought evill againſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65693:6"/> me, but God meant it unto good. Geneſ.</hi> 50.20.</p>
            <p>Nor is this ſpoken only in reference to what was already done and paſt, as ſome would ſeeme to inſinuate, who ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Verb <hi>[Totheka]</hi> in the Preſent tenſe <hi>(doth praiſe thee:)</hi> but as a Declaration of what God will ever doe, in all time to come, ſo often as the <hi>rage of man</hi> ſhall iſſue forth. Therefore the beſt Interpreters render it by the future, the rage of man <hi>ſhall</hi> praiſe thee, making it to be not onely a voice of Thankſgiving, but a concluſion of faith, as before I touched. So have you the firſt Propoſition explained. The Second followeth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The reſt of the rage]</hi> This is the <hi>Subject</hi> of the later pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which, for ſubſtance, is the ſame with the former,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Explication.</hi> The reſt of the rage.</note> to witt, <hi>the rage of man:</hi> Only it is differenced by two Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, which I muſt alike open.</p>
            <p>One of the Circumſtances is, the changing of the number in the Originall.</p>
            <p>Before it was <hi>[Chameth] rage,</hi> in the ſingular number:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> now it is <hi>[Chemoth] rages,</hi> in the Plurall; which plainely ſuppoſeth the greatnes, and the varietie of it. The <hi>rage</hi> of the wicked is not ſmall, nor terminated in one plott, or practice, nor of one kinde: but it is exceeding great, ever working, and multiplying by continuance, ſo as there can be no wicked deſigne ſo barbarous, no plott ſo bloody and Deviliſh, but the <hi>rage</hi> of Gods enemies makes them ready for it, and mad upon it. If they once miſcarry, yea if they be often diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, they are not diſcouraged, but they will to worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe, never giving over. If one Plot faile, they are ready with another, and another, of other ſorts. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and their owne hearts make them fertile and bigge with all the inventions of Hell. Juſtly then, doth the Pſalmiſt call them <hi>rages,</hi> in the Plural. For, they are as <hi>Gad,</hi> a <hi>Troop;</hi> yea, you may call their name <hi>Legion,</hi> they bee ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</p>
            <p>The other circumſtance is, in the word <hi>[Sheerith]</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, <hi>the reſt,</hi> the <hi>remnant,</hi> the <hi>remainder.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And this gives no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the abundance of it. Let never ſo much of it breake forth, yet there is ſtill move behinde, that throngs after that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65693:7"/> which got out before And, as it is with foule ſtomacks, the beſt that comes up into the Baſon, is but filthy ſtuffe, but that which is behind, and comes laſt, is farre more loathſome and bitter, through the abundance of choller and gall: ſo is it with the rage of wicked men; the beſt is abominable, but that which tarries behind, and would come up in the Rere, is moſt intolerable; that, is the bottome of the ſtomack, the dreggs, the moſt venemous and malignant part of the <hi>rage,</hi> the letting out hereof would be the deſtruction of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or ſome way or other diſhonourable to our God. This <hi>remnant</hi> it is, of which the Pſalmiſt, ſpeaking unto God, ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt restraine]</hi> This, in the Hebrew, is expreſſed in one word <hi>[Tackgor.]</hi> which imports the begirting, or binding of it in on every ſide, that it ſhall by no meanes break out, but ſhall be kept in, as a Dog in a chaine, as a Lion in his Denne, how violent ſoever. The Greek <hi>Septuagint,</hi> in their Tranſlation, have wittily expreſſed themſelves thus; <hi>the reſt of the rage ſhall keep holy day unto thee</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. Their meaning is, that as men, who are to keep an <hi>holy day</hi> to the Lord, ceaſe from labour, doing no manner of work therein, further than may directly tend to the honour and ſervice of God: ſo the rage of man, further than God may get ſome honour out of it, ſhall <hi>keep holy day</hi> too, that is, ceaſe from working or acting: it ſhall reſt from labour in regard of breaking out, how reſtleſſe ſo ever it be within, becauſe it cannot get out.</p>
            <p>But this is not all. <hi>Tremellius,</hi> in his Reviſed Tranſlation, ſupplies one word, which makes the ſenſe more complete and comfortable. For, thus Hee; <hi>reſiduo aestuum accingis (tuos)</hi> Thou doſt <hi>begirt thy people with the remainder of the rages.</hi> That is, thou doſt not onely keep in the rage of thine enemies that it doe no hurt, but thou makeſt that very rage, which was intended for their deſtruction, to become even as the walls of a Citie, for their defence and protection. The upſhot of all is this; That wicked men ſhall be ſo farre from attaining thoſe ends, which in their rage they drive at, that they ſhall be ſure to meet with a ſtop, where they made themſelves moſt ſure of going on, and be occaſions of promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65693:7"/> the good of Gods party, which they meant to deſtroy.<note place="margin">1 Obſervation</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre the Explication. The <hi>Obſervations</hi> which I ſhall now recommend unto you from the whole, bee theſe Three.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">The obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> 
               <hi>The rage of the wicked againſt God and his people is bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe and endleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Let the rage of wicked men be what it will, it ſhall onely raiſe that Glory to God, and benefit to his people, which the wicked never intended, and, ever fall ſhort of that iſſue, which they chiefly projected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The experience of Gods over-ruling, and maſtering the rage of man in times paſt, is an undoubted aſſurance of the like, for all time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The rage of the wicked againſt God and his people is bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and endleſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The rage of the wicked appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es.</note> —This is (as you have ſeene) the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of both Propoſitions contained in this Text; and that, whereof the the Godly have had ſad experience, ever ſince there was a world, and wicked men in it. It were an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriſty waſte of Time (now,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> In particular inſtances.</note> ſo pretious) to inſiſt upon the rage of <hi>Cain</hi> againſt <hi>Abel;</hi> of <hi>Eſau,</hi> againſt <hi>Jacob;</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi> and his party, againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> againſt his owne Father; of <hi>Haman,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Mordecay;</hi> of the Nobles of <hi>Babylon,</hi> againſt <hi>Daniel;</hi> or of <hi>Herod, Pilate,</hi> and the <hi>Jewes,</hi> againſt<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>Act</hi> 4.27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe. What ſhould I tell you of <hi>Davids</hi> moane,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.4.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule is among Lions, and I lie even among them that are ſet on fire;</hi> Or, of his Prayer to be<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſaved from bloody men, that lay in waite for his ſoule;</hi> Or, of his complaint of<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.11.</note> 
               <hi>many ſtrong Bulls of Baſhan, that had beſet him round?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Occaſion of this Text and Pſalme, ſpeake to this Point. The <hi>rage</hi> of <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> was firſt bent againſt <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhea,</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom, together with thoſe Ten Tribes, after three yeeres warre, hee took, and carried away Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. But,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.</note> eight yeeres after (in the Fourteenth of <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>) his wrath brake out againſt good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe: for, up he came, and ſeized into his hands all the frontier <hi>Cities of Iudah;</hi> whereof <hi>Lachiſh</hi> was one. To
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65693:8"/> appeaſe this <hi>rage,</hi> thither did <hi>Hezekiah</hi> diſpatch Ambaſſadors, and craved peace; <hi>Sennacherib</hi> propounded the Conditions and Articles; <hi>Hezeki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> accepts, and performes them. But, no ſooner was this done, but <hi>Sennacherib</hi> ſends <hi>Tartan, Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris, and Rabſhakeh from Lachiſh to Hezekiah with a great hoſt againſt Hieruſalem,</hi> and with words of <hi>blasphemy</hi> againſt God himſelfe: inſomuch as nothing was ſo eminent and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in that expedition, <hi>as</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.27.</note> 
               <hi>his rage againſt the Lord.</hi> And is it not Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> owne confeſſion of his rage againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, before his Converſion;<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 25 11.</note> 
               <hi>I puniſhed them oft in ever Citie, and compelled them to blaſpheme; and being exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mad againſt them, I perſecuted them even unto ſtrange Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 In the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of this diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Nor is this the Diſpoſition of ſome few only, but even of all the wicked. You ſee the Text is indefinite; it takes all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it. This is common to them all;<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.12.</note> 
               <hi>the wicked plotteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the juſt, and gnaſheth upon him with his teeth:</hi> not in a ſudden paſſion only, but in a conſtant premeditated courſe.<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked watcheth the righteous, and ſeeketh to ſlay him:</hi> and that,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Like a Lion that is greedy of prey, and as a young Lion, lurking in ſecret places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Againſt all the Godly.</note>Neither is this the hard hap of ſome few godly men, who through indiſcretion doe adminiſter oyle to the flame of wicked mens wrath; but even<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 59.15.</note> 
               <hi>every one that departeth from iniquity, maketh himſelfe a prey. Yea,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>and all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> And, that not onely from ſtrangers, <hi>but</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>a mans enemies ſhall be thoſe even of his owne houſe.</hi> So was it with <hi>David;</hi> witneſſe <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iophel,</hi> a Privie Counſellor, and <hi>Abſalom</hi> that<note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.11</note> 
               <hi>came forth of his owne bowels.</hi> And ſo fared it with Chriſt himſelfe; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Traitor <hi>Iudas,</hi> who was<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.7 1.</note> 
               <hi>one of the Twelve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 For godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake.</note>Nor is this, or any of this, for any real injuries done them by the godly; but even <hi>gratis,</hi> and <hi>without a cauſe,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.25.</note> except their Godlineſſe.<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>The mighty are gathered together againſt me</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) not for my tranſgreſſion, nor for my ſinne, O Lord: They run, and prepare themſelves without my fault.</hi> A thing ſo palpable in <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe alſo, that he durſt appeale to his very enemies, in the midſt of all their rage againſt him, bee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65693:8"/> fore <hi>Felix,</hi> his Judge.<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.10.5. When they rage not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, they rage the more within.</note> 
               <hi>Let theſe ſame here ſay, if they have found any evill doing in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed they doe not alwayes diſcover, and openly proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their inward rancor, becauſe all Times are not for it. And when the times would permit it, yet opportunities to ſuch and ſuch men may be wanting. In which Caſe, malicious <hi>Haman,</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 5.9, 10.</note> though <hi>fall of indignation againſt Mordecay,</hi> can <hi>refraine himſelfe,</hi> while he ſaw <hi>Mordecay</hi> countenanced by the <hi>Queen,</hi> whom he durſt not then to diſpleaſe. But yet, even then their hearts are full of deadly poyſon;<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.6.</note> 
               <hi>both the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thought of every one of them, and the heart is deep.</hi> Then, whatſoever craft or ſubtilty, Counſell or conſpiracie can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly lurke in the moſt fathomleſſe hearts of men, acted by Him who was <hi>a murderer from the beginning,</hi> doe all meet, and concentrate in them more than at other times, even when the outward face of things extort from them a plauſible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour towards the Godly.<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.24.</note> 
               <hi>He that hateth,</hi> will (at ſuch a time) <hi>diſſemble with his lips, and lay up deceit within him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as their rage is <hi>bottomleſſe,</hi> ſo is it <hi>endleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 All this, without end, or meaſure.</note> and ſtill on the encreaſing hand. <hi>Bray a foole in a morter, yet will not his folly depart from him.</hi> How often ſoever wicked men have been in plots and conſpiracies, and ſmarted for them; they wax not weary, nor give over their rage, which is like the Hare, that after once conceiving, admits of another conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, before ſhe be delivered of her former burden. The older, and more frequent they grow in villany, the more fruitfull their hearts in Deviliſh Deſignes and Inventions, till<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>their inward parts</hi> become nothing elſe, <hi>but very wickedneſſe,</hi> or <hi>wickedneſſes,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh; and, the whole frame of their ſpirits be<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 57.20.</note> 
               <hi>like the raging Sea, when it cannot rest, whoſe waters cast up mire and dirt.</hi> If any of them ſeem calmer than the reſt, it is not becauſe he is better, but becauſe more ſubtile; not becauſe he hath no minde to doe miſchiefe, but becauſe he is better able to conceale a miſchievous inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till a better opportunitie. Whence that Counſel;<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.25.</note> 
               <hi>When he speaketh faire, beleeve him not, for there are ſeven abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> This cannot be otherwiſe, for divers Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65693:9"/>1. It is the naturall bent and frame of wicked mens hearts to be miſchievous. It is their very life.<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>They ſleep not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they have done miſchiefe, and, their ſleep is taken away, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they cauſe ſome to fall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 It is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of wicked men to doe miſchiefe.</note> And in this, friends and foes are all alike to them. Sinne having turned them out of courſe, they turne out of kind; and like a mad Oxe, gore all they meet. If <hi>Herod</hi> be in his rage,<note n="a" place="margin">Macr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. li. <hi>2.</hi> Saturnal.</note> 
               <hi>as good be his ſwine, as his ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 The old em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity egges them on.</note>2. The old <hi>emnitie put betweene the</hi> two <hi>Seedes,</hi> makes the <hi>ſerpentine</hi> partie to adventure a <hi>breaking,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> yea a cruſhing of their owne <hi>heads</hi> to peeces, rather than let alone <hi>the heele</hi> of the <hi>womans ſeed,</hi> which, with all their rage, they can no more but <hi>bruiſe.</hi> Therfore wicked men, as once the<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.16.</note> 
               <hi>Philistims,</hi> take all opportunities <hi>to take vengeance with a deſpiteful heart, becauſe of the old hatred.</hi> And this <hi>emnitie</hi> is ſo hereditary, that never any Northerne High-landers more inherited the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of their Anceſtors <hi>Feides,</hi> than the whole Poſteritie of collapſed <hi>Adam,</hi> doe, the wrath and rage of their corrupt Progenitors againſt all the Godly.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3 Contrary converſation augments it.</note>3. Contrariety of Converſation augments the hatred.<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore did Cain ſlay his brother, but becauſe his owne workes were evill, and his brothers righteous?</hi> The wicked<note n="e" place="margin">Iſay. <hi>59.15.</hi> ſacit ut inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus habeatur. <hi>Tremel.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him mad,</hi> that departs from iniquitie. <hi>Therefore</hi> ſay they,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 2.12. <hi>&amp; ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Let us lie in waite for him, becauſe he is not for our turne, but is cleane contrary to our doings. — Hee is grievous to us to behold, for his life is not like other mens, his wayes are of another faſhion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The honour and happineſſe that God conferres upon his people,<note place="margin">4 Their envic a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h happines of the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly.</note> is the wicked mans envie, and addes fuell to his rage. If he muſt be miſerable, it madds him at heart to ſee them happy.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked ſhall ſee it, and be grieved, he ſhall gnaſh his teeth, and melt away.</hi> And this is not the leaſt part of the Devills own quarrell.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> For <hi>when the Dragon ſaw that he was caſt</hi> (out of heaven) <hi>unto the earth, he perſecuted the woman, caſting water after her, out of his mouth, like a flood, and making warre with the remnant of her ſeed, which keep the Commandements of God, and have the testimony of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65693:9"/>
               <note place="margin">5 The w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked hate God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. 1 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73 9.</note> 5. Their <hi>rage</hi> ſpareth not God himſelfe. Nor was it one <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> or <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> but it is the propertie of all the wicked <hi>to ſet their mouthes againſt heaven,</hi> and to be<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>haters of God.</hi> Yea, they firſt hate him, before their hatred falls upon them that be his. <hi>If the world hate you,</hi> ſaith our Saviour,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ye know that it hated me, before it hated you.</hi> And if it hate him firſt, his followers are ſure to fall under it next, and to pay for all:<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>If they have perſecuted me, they will alſo perſecute you.</hi> As good men beſtow all their<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>goodneſſe upon the Saints,</hi> becauſe they <hi>cannot extend</hi> it unto God himſelfe: ſo wicked men wreake all their teene upon the godly, the image of God (as the <hi>Panther,</hi> upon the image of a man, when he cannot come at the man himſelfe) becauſe their <hi>rage</hi> cannot reach the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſes. </seg>
               </label> You have now the Point. Many fruitfull <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> might be made of it: but I will confine my ſelf unto two or three, moſt pertinent to the preſent Occaſion.</p>
            <p>And firſt, Behold this Truth, abundantly fulfilled, this day,<note place="margin">1 Behold this in the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon.</hi> Nov. 5. 1605.</note> in your eares, through the implacable rage of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, inventing, contriving, and bringing to the very birth, this day 36. yeeres, the moſt barbarous, execrable, helliſh Treaſon that ever came within the hopes of the moſt ſavage and unnatural Aſſaſſinates, to bring forth, or conceive.<note place="margin">He wiſhed that <hi>Rome</hi> had but one neck, and that he might cut it off at one blow.</note> 
               <hi>Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> indeed wiſhed, but never <hi>hoped</hi> for ſuch a <hi>blow:</hi> and his <hi>wiſh</hi> was, a <hi>blow</hi> with the <hi>ſword,</hi> not by <hi>springing a mine</hi> from Hell. A cruelty, that he never dreamt of. Yet ſuch a Crueltie ſhould have been executed here within a few houres, had not God wonderfully <hi>reſtrained the reſt of their rage,</hi> when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was now wanting but giving fire (which alſo was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die) by the curſed hand of a ſecond<note n="*" place="margin">Faux.</note> 
               <hi>Mutius Scaevola,</hi> who (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his apprehenſion) avowed the fact, repenting of nothing but of not executing the Deſigne, <hi>wherof</hi> (as he blaſphemouſly ſaid) <hi>not God, but the Devill was the diſcoverer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed I find one <hi>Moody,</hi> a bloody Villane, ſollicited by <hi>L Ausbespine,</hi> A French Ambaſſador, of the <hi>Guiſian</hi> faction,<note n="*" place="margin">The plot was to deliver the Q. of <hi>Scots</hi> then condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. See the <hi>Annalls</hi> of the yeere, 1587.</note> to kill our late glorious <hi>Deborah,</hi> Q. <hi>Elizabeth, (An.</hi> 1587.) to have propounded the doing of it, by laying <hi>Gun-powder</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Chamber, and ſecretly firing it: And this, not above
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65693:10"/> 18.<note place="margin">1 Vſe.</note> yeeres, before the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon.</hi> But (though that were too bloody, and perhaps the Embrion of this curſed Monſter) that deſerved not to be named (for bloodineſſe) the ſame day with this.</p>
            <p>For there, only one Perſon of the Queen was aymed at; here, King, Queen, Prince, all the Nobles, Judges, Knights, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens &amp; Burgeſſes of Parliament, had all gone up at one fatall blow. There, only <hi>Twenty pound</hi> weight of <hi>Powder,</hi> in a bag or ſack, ſhould have been (but was not) provided, which perhaps might have miſcarried; but here, no leſſe than 36. <hi>Barrells</hi> were actually laid in, and covered cloſe with 1000. Billets, and 500. Fagots, not only for hiding the <hi>Powder,</hi> if ſearch ſhould be made; but, for more effectuall operation thereof, when it ſhould have been fired. There, the traiterous Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>D Ausbespine</hi> (hee diſdaining the baſeneſſe of the invention) diſliked the plot, wiſhing rather it might be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by a man of more courage (in a more generous way) like that of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by the <hi>Burgundian.</hi> But here, <hi>Garnet,</hi> and <hi>Teſmond, Garrard,</hi> and <hi>Oldcorne</hi> (or <hi>Hall</hi>) the Jeſuites could approve of the Plot, when propounded by <hi>Catesby;</hi> and for his encouragement in that worke of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">See <hi>Stat.</hi> of 3. <hi>Jac.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they joyne in the Conſpiracie as deep as any: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Report of <hi>Roger Widdrington</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Append. ad ſupplic. §. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>, a ſtrong Papiſt, to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, beſide other teſtimony.</p>
            <p>This therefore was every way Tranſcendent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all the moſt horrid Attempts wherewith any age, or Nation was ever ſtained. A fact that ſpeakes the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> and <hi>Acceſſories,</hi> not <hi>men,</hi> but <hi>Tigers;</hi> not <hi>Beasts,</hi> but <hi>Devills.</hi> The <hi>Hunnes,</hi> the <hi>Heruli,</hi> the <hi>Turcilin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> (all branded for inhumane Caiteifs in the height) were mild and temperate creatures, in compariſon of theſe. Not the ſableſt Stories, or Tragedies ever preſented ſuch a deſperate <hi>Scene.</hi> No high flowne Poet could ever reach ſuch a Plot in a fiction. In a word, <hi>Ioels</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.30.</note> Day of <hi>blood, and fire, and pillars of ſmoake,</hi> was unable to match it. Such havock of Royall and Noble Blood, ſuch heapes of daſht braines, ſuch mountaines of mangled bodies, ſuch piles of torne members, ſuch numbers of ghaſtly preys offered up to Death in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65693:10"/> could never have been thought of, much leſſe effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
            <p>This had been, beyond all preſident, inhumane and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but, the diſmall effects that muſt have ſprung from ſuch an Act, had been much more dreadfull. The deſtruction (or forcing the reſidue) of the Royall Stock, the ſubverſion of the Lawes, the ruine of the Kingdome, the utter extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing of the Light and Glory of all, the true Religion, and Profeſſion of the Goſpel eſtabliſhed among us, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing of <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſſe, <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> fornication, and <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idolatry, like a flood, to the deſtruction of ſoules, as well as bodies, had all followed at the heels of that Infernall Thunder-clap.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curſed</hi> therefore, and for ever <hi>curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath, for it was cruell.</hi> And bleſſed be that God, who hath <hi>ſcattered</hi> firſt, and <hi>divided them</hi> into peeces afterwards in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> making them an aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and an hiſſing, not in <hi>Europe</hi> alone, and among Chriſtians; but, even in <hi>Africke</hi> (that wombe of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) where very Turkes and Moores, and all ſorts of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians, that heard of this monſtrous Attempt, ſate downe amazed, their hearts melting and failing within them at the report.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if <hi>Jeſuites</hi> be conſulted, they roundly reſolve it, not only lawfull, but meritorious; So did <hi>Garnet,</hi> and the reſt before mentioned. What all the world juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes as an unjuſt <hi>rage,</hi> that they cry up as a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Zeale Of which more<note n="*" place="margin">See the later end of the next <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               </note> anon. But this is ſo farre from excuſing the fact, that it doth exceedingly aggravate the offence: for it drawes in Heaven, to father their bratts of Hell. Let them but once proclaime us <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> and they may afterwards doe any thing elſe.</p>
            <p>For our ſelves, though they brand as <hi>Heretical,</hi> thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truths profeſſed amongſt us,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 24.14.</note> 
               <hi>wee confeſſe</hi> (and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory in it) <hi>that according to that way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip wee the God of our Fathers, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all things which are written in the Law, the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65693:11"/> Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel</hi> too. And indeed, with them, this is our fault. And whereas they pronounce us <hi>ſchiſmaticall,</hi> we have often made good before the world, that wee never ſeparated from the Catholike Church, but onely from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4.</note> that we might no longer <hi>partake of her ſinnes, nor receive of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let them account of themſelves as highly as they pleaſe, and rang us among the rankeſt hereticks that ever were, they be yet to ſeek of a ſufficient warrant for ſuch a Prodigie: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we have the peremptory judgement of Chriſt himſelf to the contrary, for the everlaſting confutation of all ſuch dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrine, and the eternall confuſion of all the broachers, and abettors of it.</p>
            <p>In the Ninth of <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 51.52.</note> we finde Chriſt, in a journey from <hi>Galily</hi> to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to keep his laſt Paſſover, and to offer up himſelfe there a Sacrifice for our ſinnes; and being on the way, he ſends before to <hi>a village of Samaria,</hi> to take up ſome lodging. The <hi>Samaritans,</hi> for difference from the <hi>Jewes</hi> in Religion, but chiefly about the <hi>Place</hi> of worſhip (than which, at that time, a greater Controverſie could not happen) refuſed to entertain him, eſpecially now, that he was going up to that feaſt. And this heightned their offence of <hi>inhumanity</hi> toward a ſtranger, to an act of <hi>impietie</hi> againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; refuſing upon this ground, that <hi>he ſtedfastly ſet his face to goe to Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 53.</note> and they knew part of his buſineſſe there.</p>
            <p>His two Diſciples <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> (who perhaps had been ſent on that errand) in zeal for their Maſter, took fire <hi>at this,</hi> and preſently put it to the Queſtion;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 54.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, wilt thou that we command fire to come down from heaven, and conſume them, even as Elias did?</hi> They not only make the Propoſition, but avouch a Preſident of great authority. <hi>Elias</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.</note> did ſo upon the old <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans;</hi> therefore why not wee much more upon theſe? That wrong was but to a <hi>ſervant;</hi> this to the <hi>Son of God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: And we deſire no other revenge upon theſe, than he took upon thoſe. But what is <hi>Reſolved upon the Queſtion,</hi> by Chriſt their Maſter? Surely he gives judgement againſt his owne Diſciples, although himſelfe were moſt concerned in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65693:11"/> the Cauſe. He will not have it ſo much as attempted, no not upon ſuch impious <hi>Samaritans.</hi> For he both ſharply <hi>rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> the propounders of ſuch a fiery Motion, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 55.</note> 
               <hi>Ye know not of what spirit yee are;</hi> and refuted them too, by the end of his comming, which would not conſiſt with that Act of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as; for the Sonne of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 56.</note> 
               <hi>but to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then, if the Queſtion be at any time put, <hi>Whether a Papist may lawfully blow up a Protestant, or otherwiſe destroy him, for difference in Religion, and upon pretence of Hereſie, without Legall Triall?</hi> We can not better reſolve it according to the minde of Chriſt, than by that Reſolution, which Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe gave to a Queſtion of his owne Diſciples, to this effect, <hi>Whether it be lawfull for a beleeving Jew, yea for Apoſtles, upon wrong done to Chriſt himſelf for difference in Religion, to ſet fire on a Samaritan?</hi> Wee ſee, Chriſt is cleerely and reſolutely for the Negative: which is enough to ſecure all Cities and Villages from ſuch a Deſolation, and our Perſons from ſuch a Maſſacre, by any who truely follow Chriſt, while the World ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>Let it now be ſuppoſed by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that our Religious <hi>King, Queene, Parliament,</hi> and all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> were all out as bad as thoſe wretched <hi>Samaritans;</hi> and, themſelves as <hi>Catholike,</hi> as <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe: yet, by Chriſts Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Protestants</hi> ought to have been no worſe uſed by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> than the <hi>Samaritans</hi> by <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would Chriſt not endure that a contemptible Village of Miſcreants ſhould be deſtroyed, upon ſuch a quarrell; and yet, authoriſe theſe, to deſtroy a whole Kingdome (yea Three Kingdomes upon the matter) with one puffe, upon a farre leſſe occaſion? If he would not permit ſuch a puniſhment from <hi>Heaven,</hi> upon only <hi>Delinquents;</hi> would he approve the blowing up of many others, who, in the judgement of the Conſpirators themſelves were eſteemed <hi>Innocent?</hi> God would not ſo deale with <hi>Sodome</hi> it ſelfe, when the <hi>cry</hi> of their <hi>ſinnes</hi> called for <hi>fire</hi> from <hi>heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, if now we invert the ſcale, as juſtly we may; The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will conclude more ſtrongly. If Chriſt would not give
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65693:12"/> way to the <hi>good,</hi> to bring <hi>fire</hi> on the <hi>evill;</hi> not to <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to deſtroy <hi>hereticks</hi> and <hi>Idolaters;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Vſe.</note> nay, not ſo much as to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>fire,</hi> even from <hi>heaven,</hi> althought the Prayer were to be put up by <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> againſt <hi>Samaritans;</hi> would he warrant not only a <hi>Prayer</hi> for, but an <hi>execution</hi> by <hi>fire;</hi> not from <hi>heaven,</hi> but from <hi>hell;</hi> not by <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but by <hi>Apoſtats;</hi> not upon <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but upon ſound <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of his Truth; not by <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> whom he dearly loved, but upon <hi>Samaritans,</hi> whom all Gods people had cauſe to hate; but, by <hi>Samaritans,</hi> Prieſts and Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, Traitors and Rebells (abhorred of God and man) upon <hi>Iames</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn,</hi> very <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Church, upon the Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, &amp; upon the Aſſembly of all the Eſtates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Sober &amp; Modern Papiſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves are aſhamed of this, in behalf of thoſe furious Ones, of their own Party, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bluſh. Nay, I appeal from <hi>Garnet,</hi> to <hi>Garnet:</hi> from <hi>Garnet</hi> ſleeping, to <hi>Garnet</hi> waking: from his ſleeping Conſcience, conſulted to approve it, to his Conſcience awakened, when he was upon the <hi>Scaffold,</hi> to be executed for it. When the Queſtion was firſt put to him by <hi>Catesby, Whether it were lawfull in ſome Caſe, to deſtroy the innocent with the guilty?</hi> This Good<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Widdrington</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> Father, ſo ſoone as he apprehended the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to be in earneſt, peremptorily reſolved, that, <hi>no doubt, it was; if the good comming by it, might make compenſation for the loſſe of their lives.</hi> So that with him,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Let us doe evill, that good may come thereof,</hi> was good Doctrine, though S. <hi>Paul</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſclaim'd it.</p>
            <p>But, when he came to die, Conſcience compelled him to change his note. Then, he confeſſed to a Noble<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>E. of</hi> Manch: <hi>to whom</hi> Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net <hi>confeſſed,</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtis ſententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am juſtiſſimè in cum fuiſsè pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciatam, &amp;c.</note> Lord, yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that, <hi>for concealing this Treaſon, the ſentence of death was juſt upon him.</hi> And being led to the ſide of the ſcaffold, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the people, hee (as<note n="*" place="margin">Me in Regem peccaſſe confiteor, quod mihi eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ori, quoad mali conſcius fui, ſcil. in reticendo Et hoc nomine, veniam a Regia. Majeſtate ſupplex pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. Machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio contra Regem &amp; regnum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinolenta erat, quam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſi pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acta fuiſſet, ego ipſe in imis ſenſibus &amp; toto animo de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Dole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſane maxime &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racerbe fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, Catholicos tam atrox &amp; immanc facinus ſuſcepiſſe. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Widdrington</hi> reports him) freely ſaid, <hi>I confeſſe I have offended againſt the King, which is now my griefe, in that I was guilty of this Treaſon, in concealing of it, for which I humbly crave pardon of his Majeſtie. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracie againſt the King and Kingdome, was bloody; and had it been executed, I my ſelfe ſhould have abhorr'd it from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of my heart, and with all my ſoule. And verily, it is my greatest griefe, and with much bitterneſſe I feele it, that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65693:12"/> undertooke ſuch a cruell and outragious Villany.</hi> And, upon th <hi>Gallowes,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eoſque ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horto: ne ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi proditioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; rebellioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus contra Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmeſceant, ibid. inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> hee exhorted all Catholikes, <hi>that they would never more have hand in ſuch Treaſons and Rebellions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Soveraigne.</hi> Thus farre our firſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe:</hi> the next is this.</p>
            <p>Learne hence what to expect, as from all wicked men in general, ſo from all the brood that be <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Factors</hi> for <hi>Rome</hi> in particular; whether Lay, or Eccleſiaſtique,<note n="r" place="margin">Never expect better from them.</note> 
               <hi>Regular</hi> or <hi>Secular,</hi> to the end of the world. Surely, no better than from <hi>the rageing Sea, when it cannot rest.</hi> Nothing but <hi>rage</hi> and wrath, Conſpiracie and crueltie, Treaſon and Rebellion, ſo often as power and opportunitie meet. <hi>Whether</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.9.</note> 
               <hi>they rage, or laugh, there is no reſt.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They all lie in wait for blood, they hunt every man his brother with a net, that they may doe evill with both hands earneſtly, the Prince</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Witneſſeth Pope, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note> 
               <hi>asketh, and the Iudge judgeth for reward, and the Great man uttereth his miſchievous deſires: ſo they wrap it up. The beſt of them is a briar, the moſt upright is ſharper than a thorny hedge, &amp;c. Therefore truſt yee not in a friend, put ye no confidence in a guid, keep the doores of thy mouth from her that lieth in thy boſome,</hi> if this way addicted.</p>
            <p>What then ſhould you liſten to any of their <hi>Syrens</hi> ſongs, for <hi>abrogation,</hi> or <hi>mitigation</hi> of the Lawes made againſt them, for <hi>toleration</hi> of their Religion, or for <hi>truſting</hi> of them, as ſome would perſwade? They are no Changelings. <hi>Can the Ethiopian change his skinne, or the Leopard his ſpots?</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>then may they alſo doe good, that are accuſtomed to doe evill.</hi> I urge this the rather at this time, not only becauſe the very <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> which wee this day celebrate, rings loud in your cares, neither to truſt nor tolerate them any longer, and ſtrongly moves for a <hi>Ne admittas,</hi> againſt them; but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe alſo, even during this very Parliament, you find the old ſpirit of <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>trechery,</hi> walking too openly, and boldly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and too often preſſing too neere upon you. Let it not move you, that now they are in a Petitioning veine, and ſeem to Petition for ſome indulgence, profeſſing all Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty: For juſt ſo they gave out, while they were preparing their materialls for the Gun-powder Treaſon: then they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65693:13"/> would Petition for a <hi>Toleration of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Comming they are to manage their Cauſe, and means they have more than ordinary to advance their Party: the more reaſon, you ſhould have a more vigilant eye, and a more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive hand over them, to ſecure the King, and the Royall Seed, Religion, your ſelves, and the Kingdomes, againſt all their machinations. The better to quicken this Care in you, I ſhall humbly leave with you theſe Foure <hi>Remembrancers.</hi> Firſt, That they have never been quiet, but continually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving of Treaſons, ever ſince the Reformation of Religion. Secondly, That this practice is not from the Lawes made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Diſcourſe of the Powder-Treaſon <hi>in</hi> K. <hi>Iames</hi> his Works.</note> but their very Religion it ſelfe leades them unto it. Thirdly, That their <hi>Prieſts</hi> are bound to infuſe theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of their Religion into them, and to preſſe the uſe of them upon all occaſions. Fourthly, That to induce their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples to ſwallow thoſe Principles, and accordingly to act them when occaſion ſerveth, they propound great rewards and glory to ſuch as ſhall attempt them, and defend and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thoſe who have formerly miſcarried in them. Each of theſe I ſhall now make good unto you in order, with ſome enlargement.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">I. They have never reſted from plotting of Treaſon ſince the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
               </note>1. They have never been quiet, but alwayes hammering and contriving or ſolliciting and driving on deſperate Plotts and conſpiracies, to deſtroy their Sovereigne, to aboliſh Religion, to ſubvert the Lawes, and to expoſe the Kingdoms to a prey of any forreigne Enemie that would lend them either aide, or countenance, ever ſince the happy Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion in the glorious Reigne of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> unto this very day.</p>
            <p>It is not my purpoſe, nor will it ſuit with the ſhort limits of a <hi>Sermon,</hi> to make a relation of the <hi>Treaſons</hi> themſelves, but only to give a ſhort Catalogue of the Chiefe <hi>Actors</hi> in them, leaving the reſt to <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> who have reported them to the World.</p>
            <p>I know it goes for current, that the Papiſts of <hi>England</hi> were quiet enough for the firſt 11. yeeres of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> before any Lawes were made againſt them. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in compariſon of after times, this may be in part ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65693:13"/> to be true. Howbeit, in thoſe firſt yeeres, many of them went over Sea, and there laid the foundation of future miſchiefes here. There were others at home, that held ſtrict intelligence with thoſe abroad, doing that more ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which afterwards was more openly purſued, and avowed.</p>
            <p>It is true, that while <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth ſate <hi>Popes,</hi> their unwillingneſſe to make diſturbance here, held our Papiſts in more quiet. Yet when <hi>Pius</hi> 4. diſpatched a <hi>Nuncio</hi> to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paul</hi> 4. was Pope when <hi>Q. El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z</hi> came to the Crown. <hi>Pius</hi> 4. ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded next, and ſate t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Seventh of her Reigne. <hi>Continuat.</hi> of <hi>Martins</hi> hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, at the yeere 1561. out of <hi>Cambden</hi> their friend.</note> with a kinde meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage (as he took it;) his <hi>Nuncio</hi> could not be admitted to enter England, <hi>becauſe ſo many, bred up to the Popiſh Religion, laboured to make troubles both at home and abroad.</hi> And this happened about the Fourth of her Reigne.</p>
            <p>And if you doe but remember, from Whom, the <hi>Guiſes</hi> then procured the <hi>French</hi> King to claime the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme, and ſollicited the <hi>Pope</hi> to excommunicate the Queen; as did the Count of <hi>Foria,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in behalf of his Maſter, the <hi>Catholike King,</hi> about the ſame time; and, that divers Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Papiſts had applied themſelves to thoſe Princes; to aſſiſt in reducing the Romiſh Religion here; You will finde they had no great cauſe to boaſt of their loyaltie. Eſpecially, if you conſider that <hi>Arthur Pole,</hi> and his Brethren had no ſmall party among the Papiſts here at home, to aſſiſt in that horrible Treaſon againſt his Sovereigne, for which hee and others were after arraigned, and condemned.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth, the next Pope, mounted the Chaire, our Romaniſts began to be more active and bold. For when once his turbulent diſpoſition was knowne, the Popiſh Party, by the helpe of Cardinal <hi>Alan,</hi> firſt obtained a <hi>Colledge</hi> for Engliſh <hi>Seminary</hi> Prieſts at <hi>Doway, Anno.</hi> 1568. which indeed proved the ſeminary of all the Treaſons and Rebellions which after followed. That Colledge was after multiplied into two; one, at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> ſet up by the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> the other at <hi>Rome,</hi> erected by <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. <hi>Anno</hi> 1580. after <hi>Requeſenius,</hi> Governour of the Low Countries under the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> had thruſt them out of their firſt Neſt at <hi>Doway.</hi> And from theſe places were they upon all occaſions ſent hither, to poyſon the Subjects with Principles
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65693:14"/> of Treaſon, which every yeere produced much trouble and danger.</p>
            <p>No ſooner were they warme in their firſt Cells at <hi>Doway,</hi> but <hi>Pius</hi> 5. Excommunicated Q. <hi>Elizab.</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> abſolving all her ſubjects, and curſing all that ſhould longer obey her. <hi>An</hi> 1569. After which exploit, he ſent over his <hi>Bull Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory</hi> thereof, by <hi>Morton,</hi> an Engliſh fugitive, who bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to <hi>Ridolf</hi> a Florentine, divers Copies of it were firſt ſecretly ſcattered among our Papiſts, and then the <hi>Breve</hi> it ſelfe fixed on the Gate of <hi>London</hi>-Houſe.</p>
            <p>By which time, the Prieſts, and other active Factors for <hi>Babylon,</hi> had wrought farre upon ſundry Nobles and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of great place, whom they either found, or could make diſcontented with the preſent Religion, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or State of things, or whom they diſcerned to bee ambitiouſly affected, or moſt apt for intelligence with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes, that either maligned our Religion, envied our Proſperitie, or cunningly endeavored to poſſeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of this Crowne; which have been the deſtruction of many a Noble Spirit, and the ruine of many Ancient Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Among the many Examples of this kind, may be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the Rebellion of the unhappy Earles of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> and ſundry other their Complices, as the firſt poyſoned fruit of the Popes <hi>Bull,</hi> in the ſame yeere wherein it was heer ſcattered among the Papiſts. And from the ſaid curſed fountaine, iſſued all thoſe bitter ſtreames of Treaſons of <hi>Stukely</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> at the ſame time, of the <hi>Stanlies</hi> in <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> of <hi>Iohn Trogmorton,</hi> and <hi>Brooke,</hi> of <hi>Sanders</hi> and <hi>Briſtow,</hi> of the <hi>Nortons, Barne,</hi> and <hi>Mather,</hi> of Doctor <hi>Story,</hi> the perſecuting <hi>Civilian,</hi> of <hi>Shirwin, Parſons, Campian</hi> and <hi>Kirby,</hi> and many other Prieſts and Jeſuites, to the number of above 120. of <hi>Somervile</hi> and his adherents, of <hi>Mayne, Nelſon, Tompſon,</hi> and the reſt of that Crue, of <hi>Payne,</hi> and his 50. <hi>Reſolutes,</hi> hired by the Pope to murder the Queen, of <hi>Francis Throgmorton, Paget</hi> and <hi>Englefeild,</hi> of bloody <hi>Parry,</hi> of ſome inveigled No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65693:14"/> of <hi>Babbington, Tichborne,</hi> and the reſt of that pack, of the ſame <hi>Babington, Charnock</hi> and <hi>Savage,</hi> in a ſecond Deviliſh Deſigne, of <hi>Lopez,</hi> of <hi>Stanly,</hi> of <hi>Cullen,</hi> of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Williams,</hi> of <hi>Creſwell</hi> (who in his <hi>Philopater</hi>) and of <hi>Parſons</hi> (that in his <hi>Doleman</hi>) fomented that Treaſon of <hi>Stanly</hi> and the reſt, of <hi>Squire,</hi> of <hi>Garnet, Winter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Stat</hi> of 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Caresby, Treſham,</hi> and others, who in the laſt yeere of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> travailed with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to joyne with the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> to depoſe the Queen, and to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Religion, beſide many moe that never came to light.</p>
            <p>Nor did their <hi>rage</hi> die with that Lady, but ſo ſoone as King <hi>James</hi> came among us, <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clerk</hi> found a way to inſtill Treaſon into ſundry Nobles and Gentlemen, againſt the King and Prince, before the Coronation. And for a <hi>Coronis</hi> of all, the <hi>Salt-Peter men</hi> in the Gunpowder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (of which I have ſpoken before) can not be forgotten. I ſpare to ſpeake of their continuall Treaſons and Rebellions in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or of that memorable Deſigne in 88. which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was attempted by <hi>Spaine,</hi> yet all men know the faſt tie betweene our Papiſts and the Spaniard, their continuall correſpondencies and combinations with him, and the thundering <hi>Bull</hi> of Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> then ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, for confirmation of the ſeverall Bulls made by his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, <hi>Pius</hi> 5. and <hi>Gregory</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">He held con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation with <hi>Spaine,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vade <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> both together, <hi>An.</hi> 1576. His aime was to make his baſe Son, <hi>James Boncampagno,</hi> (Marques of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineola</hi>) King of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent zeal in a Pope! not to gain <hi>ſoules</hi> to Chriſt, but a <hi>Kingdome</hi> for his owne Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard.</note> 13. againſt Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> to the end our Papiſts might more cheerfully aſſiſt in that bloody Enterpriſe, and none dare to adhere to her againſt a forreign Enemie.</p>
            <p>Nay, let me adde, that even now, while this very Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſitting, and Papiſts Petitioning<note n="*" place="margin">See their printed <hi>Petit.</hi> in the Dial. betvveen a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> man, and a <hi>Catholike.</hi>
               </note> for indulgence and libertie, and for taking away the Lawes made againſt them, neither <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> nor <hi>Ireland,</hi> have been free from deſperate Conſpiracies and Treaſons, wherein ſundry of their Party have been principall Actors. What ſhould I tell you of the Deſignes upon the Armies in the North, of the Damnable Attempts of our Treacherous Fugitives now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and of the open Rebellion in <hi>Ireland:</hi> God grant wee heare of no more neere-hand. But yet, theſe may inſtruct you, that if you would have <hi>Peace with Rome,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65693:15"/> Rome</hi> will have <hi>no peace</hi> with you: and that, to pluck up the hedge of your Lawes, is to lay all waſte; for they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be quiet, till either by your Care and Wiſdome, you have ſecured them from doing more miſchiefe (which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, while their Idolatrie is permitted, although but in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret<note n="*" place="margin">Your <hi>Highnes</hi> may aſſure your ſelfe, that the Adverſaries wil not change their Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unleſſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we were reduced to their <hi>blindneſſe,</hi> or they drawn to imbrace the <hi>Truth</hi> with us. Biſhop <hi>Carelton,</hi> Epiſt. Dedic. to <hi>Prince</hi> (now King) <hi>Charles,</hi> before his Book of <hi>Thankfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memb.</hi>
               </note>) or till they have brought us all under the line of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that the only Reaſon of their often Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies at home and abroad, hath been the ſtrictneſſe of the Lawes made againſt them for the faults of a few, whom they condemne as much as wee: and that if thoſe Lawes (now that the occaſions of them ceaſe) were but repealed, they could, and would be as Loyall as any, notwithſtanding their Religion.</p>
            <p>I anſwere, that for the Lawes made againſt them, they may thank only themſelves, that have ſo much abuſed Royall Clemencie and Goodneſſe. But what ever the Lawes bee, none have been put to death, ſave only for Treaſon. And even among thoſe that have come within this compaſſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have eſcaped with baniſhment. And when the turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of ſome have enforced the State to execute them, yet others too guilty, have been ſpared. For, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſhortly after the proceedings againſt <hi>Campian,</hi> and ſome of his fellows,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Carelton.</hi>
               </note> ſent away 70. Prieſts in a very ſhort time out of <hi>England;</hi> ſome of which had received, and the reſt had deſerved ſentence of death for <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither have our Lawes been ſo rigid, nor ſo rigidly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> here, as theirs have been againſt <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants.</hi> Nor have Papiſts been expoſed to ſuch Butchery, as is too too frequent where Papiſts domineir. Witneſſe the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> wherinto, if any <hi>Lutheran</hi> be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly conveyed, they put him not to a legall triall, but give him their Marſhall Law. For, as <hi>Hoffeus</hi> the Jeſuite was wont to bragg, they hold it a good peece of Pietie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to commend him to the fire, <hi>ut anima ejus in curru ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo ad inferos trahatur,</hi> that ſo his ſoule might be forthwith carried to hell in a fiery Chariot; as one<note n="*" place="margin">Haſſen Muller. Hiſt Ieſuit. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> bred among them, reporteth of him.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65693:15"/>
            <p>Nay, ſundry degrees of Dignitie and honour, have been (in later times, eſpecially) heaped upon divers of them; yea they have been admitted very neere to his Majeſties Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Perſon, and truſted with Offices of greateſt honor and truſt in the State. And yet nevertheleſſe, neither any, nor all of theſe favours together, either doe, or can ſecure us of them: and that, for the Reaſon contained in the ſecond <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer,</hi> which in the next place followeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is not our <hi>Lawes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer;</hi> Their it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Religion</hi> teacheth <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> and ſo they drinke in Principles of Treaſon with the Principles of Popery.</note> but ſundry Principles of their very <hi>Religion,</hi> that makes them diſloyall, and carries them ſtill on upon Treaſons, and Rebellion, and would doe ſo, although the <hi>Lawes</hi> made againſt them, were all repealed. So that in this ſenſe, our <hi>Publike Prayer,</hi> appointed for this day, as it was firſt penned and publiſhed; <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>their faith is Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their Religion is Rebellion, &amp;c.</hi> was no ſlander, but a juſt Character of their Antichriſtian Profeſſion; and is unjuſtly altered, what ever hath been boldly ſaid, and publiſhed, to juſtifie the alteration.</p>
            <p>To make this good, I ſhall not need to ravell into all their Doctrine; but only to give you a liſt of ſuch Principles of theirs, as are obvious in all their writings, and notoriouſly knowne to all the world.</p>
            <p>And firſt,<note place="margin">Read but any of the Popes <hi>Bulls,</hi> and you need ſearch no further for proofes hereof.</note> who knows not that with them all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are condemned for <hi>Hereticks,</hi> Princes themſelves not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted. 2. That no faith is to be held with Hereticks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Hereticks themſelves are fallen from the Faith; and ſo doe forfeit all Priviledges, wherein keeping of Faith with them, might oblige others, or ſteed them. 3. That Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Princes excommunicated by the Pope, are forthwith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, and depoſed of all Princely dignitie and Soveraignty, their ſubjects are diſcharged from all alleigance, and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, if they further obey them. Witneſſe the <hi>Bulls</hi> ſent out againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by <hi>Pius</hi> 5. <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. and <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. and the writings of not onely <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> and other Forreigners, but of <hi>Alan, Saunders, Parſons, Creſwell,</hi> and ſundry other of our Apoſtate Engliſh, who have defended theſe <hi>Bulls</hi> and Poſitions, even unto death, 4. Our Engliſh Papiſts doe all profeſſe to adhere to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65693:16"/> Pope, as <hi>ſupreme</hi> in all <hi>Spiritualls</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiasticalls</hi> (their owne King having nothing to doe herein, but only in <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls;</hi>) and, to obey the Pope, before all the world, in things of this nature. 5. They know that the Pope doth profeſſe and publiſh, both by doctrine and practice, that hee hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to excommunicate the greateſt Potentates, if hereticall; to command all Catholikes in all things, <hi>in ordine ad spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alia,</hi> that have any reference to the <hi>Catholike Cauſe;</hi> that all Catholikes are bound<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bulla Pij</hi> 5. <hi>An.</hi> 1569. The Copy of which <hi>Bull</hi> you may finde in any of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, or <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> of that time.</note> to obey him (if he command it) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of damnation, in oppoſing their Soveraigne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſputing his commands; and that he hath power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all bonds, covenants, leagues and oathes, as he ſhall finde conducing to the advancement of the Catholike Faith; So that, if he liſt, no bands, humane or Divine, no oathes, never ſo ſolemnly taken ſhall binde Papiſts; for when occaſion ſerves, the Pope can, and will releaſe them from all obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God or Conſcience, of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Nations:</hi> And they muſt ſubmit unto him without regret. Nor is heer any place left for tergiverſation. For firſt, if they ſhall plead, that theſe have been the private opinions of ſome Jeſuites, and hot-ſpurres, to bring their Religion under hatred and oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie; they muſt remember, that they may not put the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Trent,</hi> nor the Popes Definitive ſentences <hi>e Cathedra,</hi> among private Opinions; if they will acknowledge any thing to be <hi>Publike,</hi> and their Pope <hi>infallible,</hi> when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees from his <hi>Chayre,</hi> which they dare not denie, without renouncing their Religion, and incurring the crime of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
            <p>If they alledge, ſecondly, as ſome doe, that <q rend="margQuotes">how ever ſome Treacherous ſpirits have been too blame, and too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Jeſuites have been Incendiaries, as well in their writings as in their practices; yet, the more moderate Catholikes have ever condemned thoſe facts and writings; and that not onely by word, but alſo by Bookes publiſhed to the world: witneſſe <hi>Widdringtons</hi> Apologie for the <hi>Oath of Alleigance,</hi> his <hi>Defence</hi> of his Apologie, his <hi>Supplication</hi> to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, his <hi>Appendix</hi> to that <hi>Supplication, &amp;c.</hi> Witneſſe alſo <hi>Watſons Quodlilets,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Catechiſme, and many
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65693:16"/> more: and laſtly, witneſſe their <hi>Petition</hi> to the preſent <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and their <hi>Proteſtation</hi> annexed, wherein they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe all ready and cheerfull obedience to the King, in all Civill and Temporall affaires; to take the <hi>Oath of Allei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance,</hi> So they be not bound to ſweare opinions; to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſclaime all forreigne Power, Papall or Princely, that ſhould pretend authoritie to aſſoile them of that Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt briefly anſwere, that albeit they have in words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed a diſlike of <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Practices, yet ſtill they hold of the Pope, for the whole frame of their Religion, and vow obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to all his publike Definitions: and, what theſe be, you have before heard in part. Next, it is true, that <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath written modeſtly, yet was he faine to purge for it to the <hi>Pope;</hi> and after all, to goe off with diſgrace. And who knows not, that ſhortly after ſome <hi>Seminaries</hi> had admired, and extolled to the heavens, the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Pius</hi> 5. againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and blaſphemouſly perſwaded the world <hi>that it was indited by the Holy Ghost,</hi> they ſet out a Booke (on purpoſe to lull the Queen and the State aſleep) to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Papiſts of <hi>England</hi> not to practiſe any miſchiefe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Queen, for that Catholikes might uſe no other Arms, <hi>but teares, prayers, watchings and fastings,</hi> againſt their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries? Yet who is ignorant of the daily conſpiracies that the Papiſts in thoſe times, and during all the reſt of Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reigne, did deſperately involve themſelves into, to their owne deſtruction?</p>
            <p>And what though <hi>Watſon</hi> and other <hi>Secular Prieſts</hi> (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of emulation and envie, than true Loyaltie) wrote ſome volumes againſt the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> when they began to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the <hi>Secular Prieſts</hi> here in <hi>England:</hi> yet this was not ſo great an argument of their fidelity, as of their ſpite and ſubtiltie: for we know that even that very <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clerk</hi> (another of his Confederates) was afterwards the deſperate propounder and ring-leader of that foule Treaſon againſt King <hi>Iames,</hi> and Prince <hi>Henry;</hi> for which hee and <hi>Clerk</hi> deſervedly ſuffered the reward of Traytors, in the firſt yeere of King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit there be lately caſt among you a Pamphlet,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65693:17"/> or <hi>Dialogue between a Parliament man and a Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like;</hi> what credit can be given to that which no man avows, no man ever preſented to you? It is, I confeſſe, a cunning piece; but, ſhamefully blending what cannot be anſwered. And it is cunningly publiſhed, perhaps for a dangerous end. If the Parliament thrive, and carry on their buſineſſe, as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; then, this Book ſhall be vouched as a faire profer of the Catholikes, rejected without conſideration. If any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſter happen, and that Romaniſts doe chance to get a Day; then, if this <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Proteſtation</hi> be preſſed upon them, they will boldly aske you, What Catholike did ever avow, or owne it? It is but a Paſquill, they will not be tyed by it.</p>
            <p>And againe, Suppoſe they take the <hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> mentioned in that Pamphlet; what are we the neerer to ſafetie, when they ſtill muſt hold that the Pope can diſpence with any <hi>Oath;</hi> and therefore with this, even when they have taken it? For, doe we not ſee them take libertie to doe ſo, with the Popes owne <hi>Bulls?</hi> Did not <hi>Parſons</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> in the yeere, 1580. (notwithſtanding their ſtrict Oath, to obey the Pope in all things) procure a Diſpenſation to free all <hi>Catholikes</hi> from obeying the Popes owne <hi>Declaratory Bull</hi> of <hi>Excommunication</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> till a better opportunitie; when as yet in the meane time, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould be under the Curſe of it, who did not preſently obey it? <hi>Quo teneam nodo?</hi> what <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Proteſtation</hi> then, will hold a <hi>Romiſh Catholike</hi> in obedience to a Prince, by them accounted <hi>hereticall;</hi> when, no <hi>Decree</hi> of the Pope himſelf ſhall hold them, if they finde it not ſeaſonable? When there is no remedy, they will yeeld to any thing: but when they ſee their time, they will doe any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> on <hi>Nov.</hi> 5. 1616. on <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi> 37.3.</note>I ſhall therefore cloſe up this, with a paſſage or two out of two Grave Authors, one a great Biſhop, in a <hi>Sermon</hi> to King <hi>James.</hi> Where ſpeaking of the prodigious Doctrine of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> in reference to the Primitive Chriſtians, and our moderne Papiſts, and of the reaſon the Cardinall gives, why the Chriſtians of old did not riſe up againſt perſecuting Emperors, <hi>Id fuit quia deerant vires;</hi> the Biſhop makes this collection, <hi>As much as to ſay, if they now in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65693:17"/> theſe daies be ſo as they were, carry themſelves quietly, it is</hi> quia non ſunt vires: <hi>and to hold no longer, than</hi> Donec e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt: <hi>and then you are like to heare of them, to have them goe againe with ſuch another birth. You ſhall have them as mild, as</hi> Gregory <hi>the First, when they have no ſtrength; but as fierce as</hi> Gregory <hi>the Seventh, when they have.</hi> And afterwards thus.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">See ye not, next under God, whereto to aſcribe our ſafety? Even to <hi>non erant vires: there is a point hangs on that For, while that laſts,</hi> while ye keep them there, yee ſhall have the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> of them; have them lie as quiet, as ſtill, as ever did the <hi>barrells</hi> in the <hi>vault,</hi> till <hi>vires,</hi> like fire come to them; and then, off goe they: then nothing but <hi>depoſe Kings, diſpoſe of Kingdomes, aſſoile Subjects, arme them againſt their Soveraignes:</hi> then, doe they care not what. But, if the <hi>Powder</hi> take not <hi>fire,</hi> thou ſhall you ſtraight have Bookes <hi>tending to</hi> mitigation; then, all <hi>quiet</hi> againe. <hi>Certainly,</hi> thus standing, it were beſt to hold them in <hi>defectu virium,</hi> to provide <hi>ut ne ſint:</hi> to keepe them at <hi>non ſunt vires;</hi> till time they be better minded in this point, and wee have good aſſurance of it. For, minded as they are, they want no will, no <hi>virus:</hi> they tell us, what the matter is; <hi>ſtrength</hi> they want; they write it, they print it, and <hi>ſi adeſſent vires,</hi> they would <hi>act</hi> it in earneſt. </q>Thus Hee.</p>
            <p>The other of my Authors having reckoned up a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the damnable Doctrines of Popery;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> on <hi>Nov.</hi> 5 on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9 19. <hi>Num.</hi> 8.</note> profeſſeth to have done it <q rend="margQuotes">to make it appeare to thoſe that would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be better perſwaded of their Doctrine, that the <hi>Doctrine</hi> it ſelfe <hi>directly</hi> warranteth <hi>Treaſon,</hi> let the Traitors be what they will, and that none can be an <hi>abſolute Papiſt,</hi> but (if hee throughly underſtand himſelfe, and live under a <hi>Chriſtian Prince,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 <hi>Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi> Popiſh <hi>Priests</hi> are bound by them, Oath, to inculcate thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
                  </note> that hath renounced the <hi>Popes Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi>) muſt needs, being put unto it, be an <hi>abſolute Traitor.</hi>
               </q> And ſo I have done with my ſecond <hi>Remembrancer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; My Third is this, that you would pleaſe to <hi>Remember</hi> that the Education and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all Prieſts and Jeſuites that come over hither under
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65693:18"/> pretence of adminiſtring Popiſh Service and Sacraments to Romiſh Catholikes, doe binde them to infuſe other principles of Treaſon into their Proſelytes, and to ſtir them up upon alloccaſions to act it. I ſhall not need to trouble you with a Liſt of the <hi>Loyaliſts</hi> Rules, nor of the Teſtimony of Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbane</hi> 8. in his Bull of <hi>Canonization</hi> of <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> touching that <hi>Societie,</hi> that beyond all other Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities, they are the Chiefe, and moſt ſtrenuous Propug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Popes Authoritie, or rather boundleſſe Tiranny. nor wil I ſtay you with a repertory of the Jeſuites <hi>Vows;</hi> and how farre that of blindfold obedience, is to be extended. The <hi>Secular Prieſts</hi> have done this at large,<note place="margin">See <hi>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſons Quodlibets,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieſuites Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars</hi> here.</note> whereby they have concluded the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> to be Traitors both for Tenets and practice here in England. I ſhall only acquaint you with what even the <hi>Seminary Priests</hi> themſelves (who are not <hi>Ieſuites</hi>) are bound unto by the Pope himſelfe, in his Conſtitutions for the ordering of the <hi>Engliſh Colledge</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof wee gave a touch before. And I ſhall give it you out of <hi>Mart. Aspilcueta,</hi> Doctor <hi>Navarrus,</hi> an Author without exception, <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Conſil. &amp; Resp. Concil.</hi> 1. <hi>de Regular. Romae in Collegio Anglorum eſt Statutum, &amp; Conſtitutio Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palis, ut quicunque illud ingredi voluerit, teneatur jurare ſe, poſt tot annos, pro defenſione fidei Catholica in Angliam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecturum, illamque ibi publicè &amp; privatè praedicaturum.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">At <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Colledge of the Engliſh, it is a Statute, and Papall Conſtitution, that whoever will be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into that Colledge, he be tyed to ſweare, that after ſo many yeeres, he will travell into England, for defence of the Catholike Faith, and there preach it both in publike and private.</q> Now what that <hi>Faith</hi> is, you have heard in part, in the former <hi>Remembrance;</hi> and, how they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and preached it here, <hi>Tiburne,</hi> and ſuch other Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits can bear them witneſſe;<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dia.</hi> between a <hi>Parliament</hi> man, and a <hi>Catholike.</hi> pag. 13.</note> And Prieſts they ſay, they muſt have, while there be any <hi>Catholikes</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> Nor can it be unknowne unto you what influence they have into the Papall ſect, of both ſexes here, what power they exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe over their Conſciences, what eſteem and honour they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65693:18"/> have among them, upon this very reaſon (among other) that theſe Prieſts are in daily hazzard of their lives, to doe them ſervice, which makes them more apt to drink down any poyſonous Poſitions that theſe Seminaries can admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to ignorant Diſciples: and ſo, under pretext of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they can, and doe at their pleaſure, wrap them up in deſperate Treaſons, ere they be aware. And whither can they not leade them by advancing the Popes Authoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, <hi>in ordine ad spiritualia,</hi> and by continually inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in their eares, that all Proteſtants are but a pack of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, which the Catholikes are ſo to look upon, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute, as the Pope ſhall command, and direct.</p>
            <p>To ſay,<note place="margin">Dial. between <hi>Parl.</hi> man, and a <hi>Cathol.</hi> p. 9.</note> that no <hi>Excommunication</hi> can <hi>deprive any man of his temporall eſtate and goods, at least in Countries where Proteſtants either are the greater part, or permitted in great numbers;</hi> is but only to caſt a miſt before weake eyes: for, firſt they know, that where the Pope excommunicates a Prince, he commands the ſubjects to riſe againſt him, as before appeareth; Next, the exception here, of <hi>Proteſtant Countries,</hi> or <hi>numbers,</hi> doth cleerly diſcover the Fox in the Lambs-Skin: for this plainly tells us, that the Popes Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures cannot take place where <hi>Proteſtants</hi> be too ſtrong for <hi>Papists;</hi> and ſo, by this you may diſcover what they will be at, when their Party ſhall ſo much encreaſe, as to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to maſter the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> as they begin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to doe in <hi>Ireland;</hi> which I hope will not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
            <p n="4">4. My laſt <hi>Remembrancer</hi> is this,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi> Corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and affections with baytes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to attempt thoſe Treaſons which their Principles doe egge men on unto.</note> That <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> doe ever corrupt the Judgements of their Followers, and Inſtruments of Aſſaſſination and Treaſon, with poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous poſitions, touching the nature of ſuch Facts; and bribe their conſciences with ſtrong baites of <hi>Reward,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> to all that will undertake the acting of Treaſons and Rebellions, at their inſtigation: which is one of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt dangerous Incentives to any new villany, that can be invented. For men that either are ſenſible of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or deſirous of glory, cannot be kept back from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65693:19"/> any Attempt, which is pronounced not onely lawfull, but noble and meritorious for advancement of their Religion. Difficultie and danger being then a whetſtone rather than a Diſſuaſive to generous mindes, thirſting after honour by publike ſervice.</p>
            <p>It hath ever been their manner to animate, not ſingle Aſſaſſinates alone (as <hi>Hall</hi> did <hi>Somervile,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> and the Cardinall <hi>de Como</hi> did <hi>Parry, Ballard</hi> did <hi>Babington, Creſwell</hi> did <hi>Stanly, Holt</hi> did <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Williams,</hi> and <hi>Walpoole</hi> did <hi>Squire;</hi>) but even all whom they can draw into any deſperate deſigne of Treaſon, by maintaining that the Act, being againſt <hi>Hereticks,</hi> is not onely juſtifiable, but commendable and glorious. Now what rewards have been promiſed to Traitors, if they doe the deed, and what glory of Martyrdome they purchaſe in heaven, in caſe they miſcarry, all our Chronicles doe amply ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Thus it fell out in the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon. Catesby,</hi> and ſome others at firſt had, or at leaſt pretended ſcruples of the Lawfulneſſe of it. <hi>Garnet</hi> and other their Ghoſtly Fathers being conſulted, pronounce it lawfull, and full of merit, and encourage them in it. <hi>Catesby</hi> had likewiſe groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe upon the Doctrine of Father <hi>Creſwell,</hi>
               <note n="b." place="margin">In <hi>Philopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> §. 2.</note> that a Prince manifeſtly hereticall, falleth from all Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power and authoritie, even before any Legall Sentence paſſed by the ſupreme Paſtor againſt him, to both which he added the infallible judgment of <hi>Clement.</hi> 8. who in two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Breves,</hi> one directed to the <hi>Catholike Nobilitie,</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the other to Father <hi>Garnet,</hi> enjoyned them not to permit any but a Catholike Prince to ſucceed Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> Hence hee concluded; Hee, who then might lawfully be kept out, may now as lawfully be thruſt out. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> enjoyned the former, <hi>Ergo</hi> we may doe the later. And thus, armed with poyſoned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, Hee and his fellowes reſolved (and indeed, who, ſo Principled, would have ſcrupled) moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to goe on with that wickedneſſe, impatient of all letts and delayes.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65693:19"/>
            <p>Thus other <hi>Traitors</hi> have found Popiſh Doctors for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to warrant their moſt deſperate Rebellions. So had <hi>Oneile</hi> firſt, and <hi>Tyroen</hi> afterwards, the publique Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Univerſitie of <hi>Salamancha</hi> in Spaine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they diſplaied their Rebellious Banners. Yea ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are the Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuites, not to ſuffer their ſeduced party to coole in their reſolute intentions of holding on any Rebellious courſe when opportunitie ſerveth, that they are ready to defend and juſtifie the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt attempts that have miſ-carried, leſt any of their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be diſcouraged by the terrible executions done upon Traitors who have periſhed in and for their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Treaſons.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that ſo many great Pens have been imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to juſtifie the <hi>Gun Powder Treaſon,</hi> and ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour conferred upon the Arch-Traitor <hi>Garnet,</hi> after his execution; and ſo much grace done at Rome to <hi>Teſmond,</hi> and <hi>Gerrard</hi> that eſcaped the hand of Juſtice here. As for <hi>Garnet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> even <hi>Widdrington</hi> complains to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, that (to the great ſcandall of Religion) His Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had permitted <hi>Garnet</hi> to be put in the Catalogue of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> his picture to be worn in Medals, his image to be ſet upon the very Altars in Churches, and his bones worſhipped as holy Reliques, &amp;c. and much ado made about a ſuppoſed ſtramineous Miracle of <hi>Garnets</hi> face found in a ſtraw, which <hi>Widdrington</hi> confutes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides. And well he might, when <hi>Garnets</hi> own <hi>Confeſſion</hi> at the <hi>Gallows,</hi> proclaimed him to be far wide of a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> as before hath been ſhewed. He likewiſe complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that <hi>Gerrard,</hi> another bird of that Neſt, had been ſeen taking of Confeſſions publiquely in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Rome under the Popes Noſe; and that <hi>Teſmond</hi> (another of the Conſpirators) was made <hi>Publique Penitentiary</hi> at Rome, and <hi>Confeſſor</hi> to the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf: and all this, after this barbarous Treaſon was diſcovered, and ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho'd over all the world.</p>
            <p>Now, what, I ſay, can the meaning of all this be, but ſtill, by impudent bolſtring up of ſuch unnaturall Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65693:20"/> to animate and encourage all Aſſaſinates and bloody Conſpirators to hold on in this Devilliſh Trade of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> when ſo ever any good ſons of his Holineſſe ſhall be called upon to do him any further Service in the like kind.</p>
            <p>Nor is it at all to be heeded that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> here do condemne it: for, openly they dare do no other, for fear of their necks: but, that in ſecret they cannot abhorre it, is manifeſt by this, that the Pope hath given not onely countenance to it, but laid the foundation of it by thoſe <hi>Buls</hi> of <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth, laſt mentioned. They muſt not condemne that, which their Infallible ſupreme Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor hath pronounced (not as a private fact, but even) <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> out of his judiciary Tribunall to be warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and neceſſarie, namely, to keep any man out of the Throne, be his Title what it will, till he take an Oath to advance their pretended Catholique Faith. For, thence <hi>Catesby,</hi> as you have heard, concluded a Warrant for that deteſtable Treaſon. And from thence all Papiſts in the Kingdome, who attribute any validitie to the Popes <hi>Buls,</hi> may draw the like encouragement for any Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie<note n="*" place="margin">So did <hi>Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> make uſe of the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Pivs</hi> 5. to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Stanly</hi> and <hi>York</hi> in the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> in delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry</hi> (a ſtrong Town pertaining to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited States</hi>) to the king of <hi>Spain;</hi> becauſe he kept it in the name of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> who had it now as a Cautionary town from the States, and ſhe (as he pretended) was deprived by the Pope of all Soveraigntie, and Dominions, and therefore <hi>Stanly</hi> did well, and others might do the like with any of the reſt.</note> and Rebellion in any time to come, againſt any Succeſſour of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that doth or ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> if the Conſpirators finde themſelves ſtrong enough, or ſubtle enough, by ſtabbing, poyſoning, blowing up, or any thing, to diſ-throne their Soveraigne, and to deſtroy all that take part with him, and endeavour to ſupport him. And ſo I have done with my <hi>Remembrancers,</hi> which I deſired to leave with you. And all that hath been hitherto ſpoken in the large proſecution of this ſecond <hi>Vſe,</hi> is but to arme you with Reſolution never to give way to any <hi>Toleration</hi> of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, or truſting of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> But this is not all: for, I muſt briefly adde,</p>
            <p>A Third <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> to exhort you all, not onely not to to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65693:20"/> Popery, or to truſt the pertinacious imbracers of it,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> but alſo to improve all your wiſedome and power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Popery, and to reduce (if poſſible) thoſe many thouſands of poore ſeduced ſouls, that, having <hi>not known the depths of Satan,</hi> are miſerably hood-winkt by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt to withſtand the light and their own ſalvation. For, till then, they will never be at an <hi>end</hi> of their <hi>Rage</hi> againſt us. And whoſoever withſtands their Idolatrie, if they have power, they will be ſure to ruine him; becauſe Popery, like <hi>Pharaohs leane kine,</hi> ſeeks to devoure all true Religion that doth oppoſe it, and all that imbrace the the true Religion oppoſite unto it. They may diſſemble, but can never put off their wrath and enmitie againſt thoſe whom they behold as Heretikes, and as men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to make fewell for hell; as, by their malicious, Idolatrous, Traiterous Prieſts and blinde Guides, they are taught to judge of us.</p>
            <p>It becomes not me to preſcribe You the way how to proceed herein, as You are a <hi>civill</hi> Body now truſted by the King and Kingdome, with all we have, but our ſouls, and our God. I know there be many excellent Lawes for this purpoſe alreadie made; and oh! that your Wiſedoms could finde out a way to their effectuall execution! But if any thing may be added, for the taking away of their children, and training them up (at the parents coſt, if they have wherewithall) in the nurture and fear of the Lord, that ſo there may not ſtill be new generations of Papiſts; I preſume it would be a Noble and Pious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for which the ſouls of many thouſands would for ever bleſſe you, by whoſe means they ſhould be delivered out of the power of that Aegyptian darknes, and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But, for our ſelves, as we are Chriſtians, let me exhort you ſtill to look upon all wicked men as having great wrath and <hi>rage</hi> within them conceived againſt us, and that we look upon our ſelves as not free from their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and fury for the future, how often ſoever they have attempted againſt us, and been diſappointed by God in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65693:21"/> all their wicked attempts. And not onely ſo, but that we carefully exerciſe our ſelves in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be prudently vigilant over our enemies, watching over them<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.17.</note> with all circumſpection and prudence; but, no way diffident of our<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.4. &amp; 9.</note> God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pray that either<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>the wickedneſſe of the wicked may come to an end,</hi> or that God would<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>breake the arme of the wicked and the evill man,</hi> and that he would<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.6.</note> 
               <hi>breake their teeth in their mouth.</hi> And if this will not do; then, that he would <hi>deſtroy them, and make them</hi> ſtill to <hi>fall by their own counſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But above all, labour to make our peace with God, and to walk humbly with him. For if the wicked be ſtill out with us, have we not the more cauſe to keep in with God? Beware of going on in any courſe of wickedneſſe, as you love your lives (to ſay nothing of your ſouls,) leſt God let looſe the <hi>ſtrong Buls of Baſan,</hi> and the <hi>young Lions</hi> that are greedy of prey, upon you. Yea, beware leſt mans <hi>rage</hi> and Gods <hi>wrath</hi> do meet, and both fall upon you at once. Oh how dreadfull muſt that needs be! If <hi>Iſrael</hi> be once a <hi>people of Gods wrath</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.6.</note>, every baſe, proud idolatrous Aſſirian <hi>ſhall tread them down like the mire in the ſtreet.</hi> Even <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſhall fall by the uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> whom before he ſlaughtered by heaps. Thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> found it in <hi>Joſhua's</hi> time. When they had once ſinned in taking of <hi>the accurſed thing,</hi> even the accurſed men of Ai ſhall be too good for them,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>three thouſand Iſraelites</hi> ſhall not be able to ſtand againſt 36. of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but flie and be ſmitten before them. But on the other ſide, if we labour to maintain peace with God, <hi>if</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>ten thouſands of people beſet us round about, we ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid: no,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>though the earth be removed, and though the mountains be carried into the midſt of the ſea; though the waters thereof roare, and be troubled, and the mountains ſhake with the ſwellings thereof.</hi> We can never miſcarrie by all the <hi>rage</hi> of all the enemies in the world, ſo long as we betray not our own ſelves into their hands. For, there is a God that ſets and orders all, as we ſhall ſee in the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65693:21"/> next point, to which I now come.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Let the rage of wicked men be what it will, it ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raiſe that glory to God, and benefit to his people, which the wicked never intended; and ever fall ſhort of that iſſue which they chiefly projected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This point hath two branches, which we muſt diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſecute.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Branch. </seg>1</label> The firſt is this, that be <hi>the rage</hi> (which is permitted to break forth) <hi>what it will,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> The rage <hi>that breaks out</hi> turns to Gods <hi>praiſe.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi> it ſhall onely raiſe that glory to God, and benefit to his people, which was never intended by the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the wicked it is as far from their hearts to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Gods <hi>glory,</hi> in their <hi>rage,</hi> as heaven from hell. If God make them<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>the rod of his anger againſt a people of his wrath,</hi> to do Gods work (not their own,) you ſhall be ſure to finde them like that <hi>Aſſirian</hi> King, who being ſent by God in ſuch an errand,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>He meant not ſo, neither did his heart thinke ſo; but it was in his heart to deſtroy, and to cut off Nations not a few.</hi> Howbeit the moſt wiſe and omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God who is alwayes zealous of his own glory and his peoples good, intends himſelf <hi>praiſe</hi> from every ſpark of fury, and extracts honour out of the leaſt atome of each mans <hi>rage,</hi> when, or which way ſo ever it break out. And this he doth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By diverting their power,<note place="margin">1. By divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</note> and driving it one way when they meant it another. Thus <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> power was imployed againſt<note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Tirhakah,</hi> when all his rage was firſt bent againſt <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> And what greater <hi>praiſe,</hi> then thus to have<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1.</note> 
               <hi>the heart</hi> and the power of ſo great a <hi>King in his hand, as the rivers of water, to turn it whither ſoever he will?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. By letting it go on till his hand may be clearly ſeen in quelling it.</note> By permitting <hi>mans rage</hi> ſometimes to proceed ſo far, as all may ſee a neceſſity of a Divine Power to give it a ſtop, and behold an immediate arm of the Almighty in defeating of it. Therefore God permitted <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to purſue <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not onely to the banks, but even into the midſt of the <hi>Red ſea,</hi> that by deſtroying him there,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xod.</hi> 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>the right hand of the Lord might become more glorious in power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65693:22"/>3. By extorting from his enemies an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his power and conqueſt, in the midſt of their <hi>rage.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. By making his enemies confeſſe he is againſt them.</note> So he did, from that <hi>Dragon</hi> and his hoſt which <hi>he ſlew in the Sea,</hi> when they cried out,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.24.</note> 
               <hi>Let us flee from the face of Iſrael, for the Lord fighteth for them againſt the Egyptians.</hi> And ſo, from that Atheiſticall <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> who ſeeing the terrible diſſipation of that <hi>Invincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado,</hi> in 88. profeſſed that <hi>now he perceived God was turn'd Lutheran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. By more <hi>praiſe</hi> from his own people,</note>4. But more eſpecially doth God receive honour and praiſe from his own, whom he delivers from the <hi>rage of man.</hi> Thus did he, from Iſrael, <hi>when they</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.30.</note> 
               <hi>ſaw the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans dead upon the ſhore.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.12.</note> 
               <hi>Then beleeved they his words, and ſang his praiſes.</hi> Yea then, they proclaimed him<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.11.</note> 
               <hi>fearfull in praiſes doing wonders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">5. By produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing effects contrary to the intentions of wicked men.</note>5. In producing effects of <hi>mans rage,</hi> quite contrarie to thoſe which men intended and expected. If <hi>Joſephs</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren will <hi>ſell him,</hi> his bondage ſhall procure his advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yea, and (though they deſerve it not) their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20.</note> 
               <hi>As for you</hi> (ſaith he to them) <hi>ye thought evil againſt me, but God meant it unto good, to bring to paſſe as it is this day, to ſave much people alive.</hi> If <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt be caſt out into the mud to ſatisfie <hi>Pharaohs</hi> crueltie, even <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> daughter ſhall preſerve him<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4, 16.</note> 
               <hi>to be unto Pharaoh in ſtead of a God,</hi> to plague <hi>Pharaoh</hi> while he lived, and then to be an inſtrument of his deſtruction, by that very ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould have periſhed. When the bloody plot of <hi>Haman</hi> for the deſtruction of <hi>all the Jews,</hi> drew neer to execution, not onely himſelf and his ten ſons handſelled that very gallows which he had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for <hi>Mordecai;</hi> but even all<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>the enemies of the Jews who hoped to have power over them,</hi> found all <hi>turned to the contrary,</hi> and <hi>that the Jews had rule over them that hated them.</hi> If the <hi>rod of the wicked</hi> light on the backe of the righteous for ſome ſin againſt God, this alſo ſhall <hi>turn</hi> much <hi>to his praiſe:</hi> for<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.9.</note> 
               <hi>by this ſhall the iniquitie of Jacob be purged</hi> (to prevent deſtruction intended by the wicked;) <hi>and this is all the fruit, to take away ſin,</hi> which <hi>mans rage</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65693:22"/> never meant. Yea, if the <hi>rage</hi> prevail ſo far as to be the death of the righteous; yet even this alſo ſhall turn <hi>to his praiſe,</hi> by cauſing the death of one righteous man for righteouſneſſe ſake, to be the ſeed of many moe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that ſhall riſe up in his roome. Never ſuch an increaſe of ſhining Chriſtians, as when Chriſtianitie is under ſharpeſt perſecutions, And, as for ſuch as <hi>looſe their lives for Chriſts ſake,</hi> they are ſure<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>to ſave them;</hi> that is, for ever to live in glory: ſo that, for them<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>to die is gain;</hi> and,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>in all theſe things they are more then Conquerors through him that loved them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus every way, <hi>the rage of man</hi> brings honour to God, and good to his people; and that upon theſe grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 1. God never put power into the hands of wicked men, but for his own holy ends. Therefore,<note place="margin">Wicked mens power is onely for Gods ends.</note> if they uſe that power to rage againſt his ſervants, he muſt and will carrie on his own work, let them intend what they liſt. Now, Gods end in raiſing ſuch men is,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>to ſhew in them his power, and that his Name may be declared in all the earth.</hi> How, but by his<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>getting honour upon them</hi> in the ſtrongeſt purſuit of their rage againſt the godly, as he did upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his <hi>hoſt,</hi> when they would have devoured <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 2. God cares not a ruſh for the greateſt and proudeſt <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> in the world that rage againſt his people,<note place="margin">God will break the wicked rather than they ſhould hurt the godly.</note> in compariſon of any one poore ſervant of his own op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by them:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14.</note> he will <hi>ſuffer no man to do them wrong,</hi> but will <hi>rebuke even Kings for their ſakes</hi> that rage againſt them; yea,<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>break them to pieces like a potters veſſell,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.14.</note> and <hi>ſcatter them</hi> like hay in a whirl-winde, or ſhips in a tempeſt, rather than not make his people gainers by their <hi>rage.</hi> So he dealt with <hi>Pharaoh, Sennacherib,</hi> and many moe. This being his peremptorie reſolution, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>all things ſhall work together for good to them that love him;</hi> and therefore, <hi>the rage</hi> of the wicked, how much ſoever they hate them.<note place="margin">God outſhoots them in their own bowe.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 3. God delights to out-ſhoot the wicked in their own
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65693:23"/> Bowe. If<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 37.14.</note> 
               <hi>they bend their bowe, to ſlay ſuch as be of upright converſation,</hi> he will ſhoot that arrow of their wrath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ever they intended it, and ſtick it faſt in their own boſomes.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.5.</note> If <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſhoot at <hi>Iſrael</hi> Gods <hi>firſt-born,</hi> the arrow ſhall fall ſhort; but then, God takes it up, and he ſhoots it into the very heart of <hi>Pharaohs</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>firſt-born,</hi> and he is ſure to die for it. Thus, if the devill will ſtill animate the <hi>rage</hi> of <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>the people of the Jews</hi> to kill Chriſt, that very arrow which gave Chriſt his deaths wound, ſhall be the<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>death of death</hi> it ſelf, and the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>grave,</hi> and give the greateſt blow to the devil and his kingdome that ever he received. Little thought Satan when in his rage he proſecuted Chriſt to death, that the death of Chriſt ſhould be the ſaving of a world, the reſcuing of many millions of ſouls out of his power, and the deſtruction of the kingdome of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But ſo home did God ſhoot this ſhaft, out of the bowe of his <hi>Croſſe,</hi> that<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb</hi> 2.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>by death, he destroyed him who had the power of death, that is, the devill; and delivered them who, through fear of death, were all their life time ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now given you the firſt branch of the Point, the other follows, which in effect is this,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Branch. </seg>2</label> The rage of the wicked ſhall never extend ſo far as to do the work they intended,<note place="margin">God makes mans rage fall ſhort of their aime.</note> 
               <hi>but ſhall ever fall ſhort of that which they chiefly projected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true that their <hi>rage</hi> ſometimes goes very far, and doth much miſchief; but never beyond what may ſtand with the honour, truth, and goodneſſe of God, and with his Covenant made to his people. When the enemie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to make himſelf ſure of his will upon the godly, and to ſay,<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.9.</note> 
               <hi>I will purſue, I will overtake, I will divide the ſpoile; my luſt ſhall be ſatisfied upon them, I will draw my ſword, mine hand ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> Then God ſteps in, and ſets their bounds far ſhorter then wicked men promiſed to themſelves, ſaying to them, as to the raging ſea,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 38.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſhalt thou come, but no further: and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtayed.</hi> And this he doth many waies.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65693:23"/>1. Sometimes by filing off the edge of that roughneſſe and malice that is in them, and conſtraining them to mildneſſe and gentleneſſe, contrary to their very natures,<note place="margin">1. By filing off their roughnes and malice.</note> and ſetled reſolutions long before taken up. Thus he <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the rage</hi> of<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.22.</note> 
               <hi>Laban</hi> againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28.</note> who ſhortly after alſo, as <hi>a Prince prevailed with God,</hi> to <hi>prevail</hi> with <hi>Eſau,</hi> that had long vowed his death; ſo that at their meeting, the rage and malice of <hi>Eſau</hi> was tyed up, and<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob ſaw his face as if he had ſeen the face of God,</hi> ſo well was <hi>Eſau pleaſed with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes,<note place="margin">2. By giving them work elſewhere.</note> by giving them ſo much work elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, that they have neither leiſure not power to purſue the godly any further. We ſaw it<note n="e" place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.8.</note> before in <hi>Sennache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib:</hi> and we may ſee it in<note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> at <hi>Ramoth-Gilead,</hi> when he intended a further perſecution of <hi>Michaiah;</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>Iulian,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Greg. Naz. Orat. <hi>4.</hi> in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</note> who reſolving to deſtroy all the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> found a neceſſity to go firſt againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> by whom he was overthrown; and ſo, diſabled from ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his <hi>rage</hi> upon the others. Thus God often gives Tyrannicall Princes buſineſſe enough abroad, when he findes them ſtudious to deſtroy their beſt Subjects at home.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. By ſpoiling them of the inſtruments of revenge.</note> Sometimes by diſpoiling them of the Inſtruments whereon they relie, as<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.25.</note> 
               <hi>he took off the chariot wheels of the Egyptians</hi> in their purſuit of Iſrael: either by rending from them a great part of their Dominions; as, from<note n="h" place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> when he reſolved to go on in his oppreſſion of his petitioning Subjects; or by weakning that ſtrength which remains with them, as he did that of the <hi>Aſſirian</hi> when he thought none could ſtand before him,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>ſending among his fat ones leanneſſe, and under his glory kindling a fire:</hi> or by infatuating their counſels making<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Zoan fools, and the wiſe Counſellers</hi> of a perſecuting <hi>Pharaoh to become brutiſh,</hi> and cauſing them to fall by their own counſels, as<note n="l" place="margin">Theodor. hiſt. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iulian</hi> before the <hi>Perſians,</hi> when, in a bravado, he would needs burn his ſhips, to put the more neceſſitie of valour into his Souldiers; or by infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating themſelves, that they cannot underſtand good
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65693:24"/> counſel when it is before them (as in <hi>Rehoboam</hi> caſe<note n="*" place="margin">1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.</note>) but rather follow that which is directly given for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and to countermine their own plots; as, when<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Abſolon</hi> followed the adviſe of <hi>Huſhai</hi> againſt that of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> which would have carried his deſigne that <hi>Huſhai</hi> by his counſell prevented. And indeed this is one of the greateſt <hi>misfortunes of a Prince</hi> (as a grave<note n="n" place="margin">Phil. de Co. min. ll, <hi>5.</hi> c. ult.</note> Author ſpeaketh) and a ſad ſymptome of his approaching ruin, <hi>when God ſmites him in his wits,</hi> as he did <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> to <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the counſels of thoſe who were brought up with him,</hi> and knew how to fit his humour, and to reject the counſels of graver men, who adviſed nothing but for his proſperity, and honour.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. By arming his creatures againſt them.</note>4. By arming his creatures againſt them to ſuppreſſe their rage; as, he did the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſtars,</hi> againſt <hi>Siſera;</hi> the <hi>waters, frogs, lice, flies, hail, locuſts,</hi> and other things againſt <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and, even an <hi>Angel,</hi> againſt the <hi>host</hi> of <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib.</hi> Thus God raiſed a mighty winde from heaven againſt<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei. li. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Tyrant, that beat his Souldiers weapons out of their hands, when they were to fight againſt the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> under <hi>Theodoſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">5. By panick fears.</note>5. By panick fears and ſtrange apprehenſions without any ground: as, a meere caſuall <hi>dreame</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.13.</note> of a <hi>Midianite</hi> frighted an innumerable army, and rendred them unable to ſtand before 300 unarmed men. So the <hi>Moabites</hi> were overthrowne by occaſion of<note n="r" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 3.22, 23.</note> a <hi>colour of blood</hi> upon the waters cauſed by the <hi>Sun,</hi> riſing very red in the morning, and <hi>ſhining on the waters</hi> between the <hi>Sun</hi> and them.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">6. By making them fall one upon another.</note>6. By ſetting the enemies of his people one againſt another. Thus, in that great hoſt of <hi>Midian</hi> and <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck,</hi> that came out againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.22.</note> the <hi>Lord ſet every mans ſword against his fellow throughout all the hoſt.</hi> And the like we have read in <hi>Iehoſhaphats</hi> time, when<note n="t" place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Ammon, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Mount Scir</hi> deſtroyed each other.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">7. By ſetting them againſt themſelves.</note>7. By turning their own ſwords upon their own breſts. Thus <hi>Achitophel, Judas, Pilate, Nero,</hi> and others have done.<note n="u" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>Achitophel</hi> hanged himſelf when his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65693:24"/> for the deſtruction of <hi>David</hi> was rejected.<note n="v" place="margin">Mat. <hi>27.5.</hi> Tertul. Apolo. cap. <hi>5.</hi> Euſeb. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>7.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> did the like, when he had betrayed his Maſter. <hi>Pilate</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demner of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> the perſecuter of Chriſtians, did both fall by their own hands, without effecting what either the one or the other had mainly intended.</p>
            <p n="8">8. By diſcovering their cloſeſt plots and counſels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they take effect: and a Treaſon diſcovered is loſt. Thus did he diſcover the plot of<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Haman</hi> againſt the <hi>Iews;</hi> of the<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>Iews</hi> againſt <hi>Paul;</hi> And ſo God did ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open that plot of the <hi>Earles</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> combining with the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by a ſtranger without the Kingdome; in ſo much as the <hi>Pope</hi> openly ſaid,<note n="z" place="margin">Hieron. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenae, ubi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>That never any Conſpiracie was more advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly begun, nor concealed with more conſtancie and conſent of minds, being not at all opened by any of the conſpirators.</hi> Thus doth God provide, that rather then the <hi>rage of man</hi> ſhall take place, to his diſhonour,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>a bird of the aire ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may take the <hi>Reaſons,</hi> in a word.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">1. Becauſe Gods power will carry on his own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</note>1. The power of God is ſuch, that whatſoever<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> be found <hi>in the hearts of men, yet the counſell of the Lord that ſhall ſtand.</hi> Let their <hi>rage</hi> be what it will; yet, not theirs, but <hi>Gods will muſt be done.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.30.</note> 
               <hi>There is no wiſedome, nor underſtanding, nor counſell against the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. All wicked men, and devils are in Gods hand:<note place="margin">2. All men &amp; devils are in Gods hand.</note> and how furiouſly ſoever they <hi>rage,</hi> yet they can run but to the end of their chain. They may <hi>rage,</hi> but<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.4.</note> God <hi>laughs them to ſcorn.</hi> The devill himſelf may lay about him, but God holds him in his hand: ſometimes<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>bruiſing him,</hi> ſometimes<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rvel.</hi> 20.2.</note> 
               <hi>binding him:</hi> but alwayes maſtering and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering him, that<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>the gates of hell ſhall not prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Church</hi> and people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God is engaged by promiſe to his people that keep his wayes,<note place="margin">3. Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is to beat down all wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</note> that<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.17.</note> 
               <hi>no weapon that is formed againſt them ſhall proſper, and every tongue that ſhall riſe up againſt them ſhall they condemne;</hi> and, he pronounceth <hi>this to be the heritage of the ſervants of the Lord.</hi> Therefore God is bound to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65693:25"/> 
               <hi>reſtrain</hi> all that <hi>wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the ſecond <hi>Point.</hi>
               </note> which would enervate the faith of his people in ſuch a promiſe, and diſappoint them of performance.</p>
            <p>Thus, having given you both <hi>branches</hi> of the <hi>ſecond point,</hi> I deſcend to the <hi>Vſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Vſes.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Behold all this fulfilled to our ſelves.</note>And firſt, Behold, all this fulfilled this day, not in our <hi>cares</hi> onely (as the <hi>Treaſon</hi> was) but in our <hi>eyes</hi> too. What the <hi>Rage of man</hi> upon this day, was, you have alreadie heard. Now ſee how this <hi>rage</hi> ſo far as it was permitted, did <hi>turn to Gods praiſe,</hi> and how powerfully he <hi>reſtrained the reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Their</hi> rage turned to his praiſe.</note>How ſtrongly was their plot laid! how ſecretly, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried! how neer, the execution! how probable, the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe! how confident the Inſtruments, of their expected iſſue! How boldly did they vaunt, that they had gotten <hi>God</hi> himſelf into the Conſpiracie! <hi>God and man had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to puniſh the wickedneſſe of that time,</hi> ſaid the Author of that Letter which occaſioned the miſcarriage of all, miſtaking the <hi>Devill,</hi> for <hi>God.</hi> Yet even then, we ſee how admirably God <hi>turned</hi> all this <hi>rage to his praiſe,</hi> by <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of thoſe that were appointed to die,</hi> and by giving them up as a prey to death who had deſtinated ſo great a ſacrifice to <hi>Death</hi> of ſo many at once. Inſomuch as the greatneſſe of the danger did not more ſmite the world with a juſt amazement, than the extraordinarineſſe of the deliverance took all men with high admiration.</p>
            <p>God permitted it ſo far that all might ſee his hand as clearly in the reſcue, as in the deliverance of <hi>Daniel,</hi> in the <hi>Lions den;</hi> and his judgement on the Traitors, as in the deſtruction of <hi>Daniels</hi> enemies by the ſame creatures that touched not him. One ſpark of fire flying out of the Chimney where they were drying <hi>powder</hi> to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, firſt brought divers of the principall Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (by the wounds received from the <hi>powder</hi> kindled by that ſpark) to acknowledge the juſtice and vengeance of God upon them by <hi>powder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">At <hi>Holbeach</hi> in <hi>Worceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
               </note> wherewith they intended the deſtruction of ſo many. And afterwards, <hi>Catesby and Piercy,</hi> the principals in that wickedneſſe, were ſhot to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65693:25"/> death by one ſhot of a <hi>Musket,</hi> and thereby found Gods own hand taking revenge by <hi>powder,</hi> before the juſtice of man could ſeize upon them. And not onely ſo, but even <hi>Faux</hi> the appointed <hi>Executioner,</hi> and <hi>Garnet</hi> (the Arch-Devil to bleſſe their plot) confeſſed to the <hi>praiſe of God</hi> as well as the reſt at their execution, the outragious wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and odiouſneſſe of that helliſh deſigne.</p>
            <p>Nay further, God raiſed up an everlaſting<note n="*" place="margin">An <hi>Act</hi> for keeping of this Day, for ever.</note> Pillar of <hi>Thankeſgiving,</hi> from that very <hi>Parliament</hi> which ſhould have been blown up; and produced effects quite contrary to thoſe which the Traytors intended, in preſerving not onely the <hi>Perſons,</hi> but the <hi>Laws,</hi> which they meant to deſtroy, and in cauſing moe <hi>Lawes</hi> to be made againſt them who ſo wickedly provoked the Clemencie of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and abuſed the lenitie and mercie they formerly enjoyed; but, in providing more carefully, ever ſince, for our preſervation.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you that, <hi>the reſt of the rage</hi> is happily <hi>reſtrained.</hi> Your eyes behold it, and we all ſit under the bleſſing of it unto this day. Onely take notice, that God did it, not by <hi>ordinary</hi> meanes.</p>
            <p>Not <hi>by abating th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir rage:</hi> for <hi>Faux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">God <hi>reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the rest,</hi> not in an ordinary,</note> after his appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, repented nothing more then his not giving the blow; yea the whole crew afterwards brake forth into open Rebellion, till ſome of them were ſlain, and the reſt taken, in the height of their <hi>rage.</hi> Not <hi>by diverting them;</hi> for they received not the leaſt interruption, till all was ready for execution. Not <hi>by taking off any of their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> for, not a man of them was toucht by death, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or arreſt, till after the very trains were laid to the powder, and all prepared for the firing of it. Not <hi>by arming the creatures againſt</hi> them: for no creature once troubled them, till they were found out (almoſt too late) to be <hi>Troublers of Iſrael.</hi> Not <hi>by ſmiting them with Panick fears:</hi> for they were never ſo high floan (before the diſcovery) with confidence of ſucceſſe, nor more deſperately fearleſſe, after they knew that all was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Nor yet, <hi>by ſetting them one againſt another:</hi> for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65693:26"/> (like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi>) they held too faſt together,<note place="margin">2. Uſe <hi>of the ſecond</hi> Point.</note> even unto death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">but in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner.</note>But the Lord did it himſelfe, cauſing one of them (who had taken three <hi>Oaths</hi> to conceale it, and kept touch with his <hi>tongue</hi>) by a <hi>writing</hi> to reveile it; verifying that of the Wiſeſt King, that,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter;</hi> and, affecting the King with a ſpirit of jealouſie, (who ordinarily offended rather on the other hand) and leading him to an interpretation of the <hi>Letter,</hi> quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the common ſenſe. And not onely ſo, but by ſharpning the edg of all mens ſpirits againſt the <hi>Traitors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> of the <hi>Powder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in King <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Works.</hi>
               </note> in the Countries where they wandred, to kill ſome of them, and to apprehend the reſt, even before any <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> could overtake them, and before the people who ſeiſed on them, knew any thing of this particular <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Thus, <hi>He that ſitteth in the Heavens, laught them,</hi> their <hi>rage,</hi> and <hi>Counſels,</hi> to ſcorne; compelling them, at length, to acknowledge the <hi>finger of God</hi> in their <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery,</hi> and his <hi>arme</hi> in their moſt deſerved <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> O wonderfull <hi>Providence!</hi> O admirable <hi>Justice</hi> upon them, and <hi>Goodnes</hi> to his People!</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Uſe <hi>of the ſecond</hi> Point. Incitation to thankfulnes.</note>2. How ſhould this put all our hearts into a flame of the higheſt Thankſgiving to Him who hath done for us ſuch wonderfull things! When their <hi>Rage</hi> had concluded that We and all Poſterity ſhould for ever wallow in aſhes,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nah.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>taber upon our breaſts,</hi> and howle like Dragons for that irreparable Deſolation; the God of our Mercies hath prevented them, broken the ſnare, given us an eſcape, and hurl'd them out of the <hi>Land of the Living,</hi> as <hi>out of the midſt of a Sling.</hi> Therefore, rejoyce <hi>in the Lord, and againe I ſay rejoyce:</hi> Rouſe up your ſpirits, call up your hearts, <hi>and let all that is within you bleſſe his holy Name.</hi> I hope I ſhall not need to ſet before you <hi>the Inſtitution of a thankefull man;</hi> nor, to ſpend time in <hi>directing how to give thankes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">On Septem. 7. 1641.</note> that Work being excellently performed at your late <hi>Publique Thanksgiving.</hi> Rather let me beſtow a few words to incite you to the Duty, becauſe I finde every where more and more backwardneſſe to it, and coldneſſe in it.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:65693:26"/>
            <p>For, however, at firſt, the meltings of moſt mens ſpirits were extraordinary (their affections being ſoone upon the wing,<note place="margin">The <hi>neceſſitie</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation.</hi>
               </note> when the firſt newſe of the <hi>Deliverance</hi> out-ran the report of the <hi>Danger.</hi>) Yet, by Degrees men have ſo farre cooled, that not onely too many of the ordinary ſort doe wholly neglect this Day; but, not none of the Clergy alſo, who have ſometimes (for their hyre) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed vehemently againſt that <hi>Treaſon,</hi> in the Pulpit, begin in ordinary diſcourſe to jeere this ſolemnitie of ſuch a <hi>Deliverance;</hi> and, in deriſion, to name it, <hi>Saint Gunpowders Day.</hi> Papiſts perſwade their Novices that there was never any ſuch thing. Yea, ſome (once ours) have arrived at ſo much giddineſſe, as to pronounce the keeping of this <hi>Day</hi> to be <hi>Will-worſhip;</hi> and, the religious enjoyning of it, even by <hi>Parliament,</hi> to be a trenching on the <hi>Libertie</hi> left us by Chriſt; as if the <hi>binding</hi> of our ſelves (as Gods people of old, in their feaſt of<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Esth.</hi> 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>Purim,</hi> did) to give publique thanks for an extraordinary Mercy, were a violation of true Chriſtian Libertie. O ſhamefull Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude! O Impudent Ignorance! And how careleſſe the greater part of the better ſort are become in obſerving this Day, is a ſubject more fit for my teares than my tongue, even in this Honorable Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, the better to quicken You, to reſtore this Day to its former ſplender,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motives</hi> to the <hi>Duty.</hi>
               </note> that the Great <hi>Work of the Lord</hi> done herein, may be for ever more <hi>honorable, and glorious,</hi> Let Me preſent You with a few Incentives.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Remember that,<note place="margin">1. None but God could doe it.</note> none but the Almighty himſelfe could poſſibly have wrought ſuch a <hi>Deliverance</hi> for us.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide when men roſe up againſt us, they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled againſt us.</hi> Let this firſt ſettle upon our ſpirits, that<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>this was the Lords doing,</hi> and then it will ſoone be <hi>marveilous in our eyes,</hi> ſo as <hi>Wee</hi> cannot but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and be glad in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Think ſeriouſly what manner of perſons wee were,<note place="margin">2. He did it for people altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unworthy of any mercy.</note> for whom he did all this. Are we not a ſinfull, unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſtubborne People, as ever taſted of mercy? a <hi>ſeed of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65693:27"/> evill Doers,</hi> that call God<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Father, and yet doe as evill things as we can?</hi> And yet for all this, God hath opened his <hi>hand wider,</hi> than ever we <hi>opened our mouths,</hi> and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all our yeares and dayes with ſuch loving kindneſſe and mercy, as never any Nation under Heaven received greater, or enjoyed longer. If therefore <hi>David,</hi> upon the bare promiſe of a mercy, could not but <hi>ſit downe before the Lord,</hi> as one in an Extaſie, crying out, <hi>Who am I O Lord, and what is my Fathers Houſe, that thou haſt brought me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto?</hi> How much more would our ſpirits be lifted up beyond all expreſſion, to glorifie his Great Name for ſo great a mercy actually conferred, when we conſider who and what we are that doe receive it!</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. The delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary.</note>3. Look upon the Deliverance it ſelfe as extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>All the</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.2.</note> 
               <hi>Works of the Lord are great:</hi> yet, ſome grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than others; But this is no leſſe than <hi>the rayſing up of a whole Kingdome from the dead.</hi> For, as<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>received</hi> his <hi>Iſaac from death in a figure,</hi> when <hi>Iſaac</hi> had been bound on the wood, and the hand of his owne Father ſtretched out to kill him; ſo wee, in this Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, received our King, Queen, and Prince that then were, our King that now is, our Parliament, Lawes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Lives, and Religion it ſelfe from the dead in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, when all theſe were ſo neere to deſtruction that there was ſcarce a <hi>ſtep between them and death,</hi> and ſuch a ſtep as had been eaſily made, had not the Lord <hi>to whom belong the iſſues from death,</hi> ſtept in to prevent it.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. And altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>unexſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</hi>
               </note>4. Take this with you too, that this great <hi>Deliverance</hi> was a mercy altogether unexſpected. (For, who appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended any danger?) The work was ſo ſtrange, as wee could hardly credit when we ſaw it done. It was with us, as with <hi>Zion,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1.</note> 
               <hi>When the Lord turned her Captivitie</hi> by <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the <hi>Perſian;</hi> Wee were <hi>like men that dreame:</hi> we could ſcarce truſt our owne eyes to behold it, or our tongues to proclaime it. Men gazed on each other as people ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. And when the thing was found to be ſo indeed, oh how our hearts glowed! our affections fired! our hayre ſtood upright! our eyes ſparkled! our joynts trembled!
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65693:27"/> our ſpirits even failed with us to behold the wonder! And then, oh what might not God, at that time, have had from us! Let him therefore not goe away now with leſſe; ſeeing <hi>his Mercy,</hi> even that <hi>Mercy endures for ever,</hi> to our benefit and comfort.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Behold the Love of God in it,<note place="margin">5. And all this as a fruit of his <hi>Love.</hi>
               </note> makes all to be yet more precious to a thankfull ſpirit.<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 43.4.</note> 
               <hi>I have Loved thee, therefore will I give men for thee, and people for thy life,</hi> ſaith the Lord. If <hi>men,</hi> yea, if a whole Nation conſpire againſt thy life, he will redeem thee from that danger with the price of all theirs. Hence it is, even from his <hi>Love,</hi> that he no ſooner eſpies any enemies out againſt us, but he armes preſently as againſt enemies to himſelfe; and, not onely Layes them at his own feet, but even at<note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam</hi> 22.41. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>ours,</hi> and gives us to <hi>waſh our feet in the bloud of the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider, God hath gotten him <hi>honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. God hath gotten him praiſe from the <hi>wicked</hi> that ſought our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note> and rayſed himſelfe a <hi>praiſe</hi> out of the very <hi>rage</hi> of thoſe who ſought our deſtruction, and ſhall he not have it from thoſe who enjoy this miraculous Preſervation? Shall he have it from his <hi>enemies,</hi> and goe without it from his <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Friends?</hi> The Lord forbid.</p>
            <p>But oh! farre, and for ever farre be ſuch neglect from every of You, who being <hi>the Chariots of Iſrael and the Horſemen thereof,</hi> ought of all others to <hi>triumph in his praiſe</hi> for theſe <hi>works of his hands.</hi> It was a foule Blot to the <hi>Elders of Judah,</hi> that, after <hi>David</hi> was freed of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of <hi>Abſolom</hi> they, who were<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>his brethren, his bones and his fleſh,</hi> ſhould be <hi>laſt in bringing back the King to his Houſe.</hi> But much greater would the ſtaine and the ſinne be in You <hi>the Elders</hi> of our <hi>Jſrael,</hi> unto whom the Lord himſelfe (upon the ſame grounds that he hath elſewhere ſaid,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are Gods,</hi>) now ſaith, <hi>Yee are my brethren, yee are my bones and my fleſh,</hi> ſhould have cauſe to adde, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then are yee the Laſt to bring the King back?</hi> Why are You ſo backward to reſtore unto Him all that honour that ſo many <hi>Abſoloms</hi> and ſonnes of Rebellion have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Him? Well, If you be not firſt, nay if You out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip not all others in the Duty of <hi>Praiſe</hi> for ſo great a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65693:28"/> Deliverance from <hi>the rage of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> You muſt exſpect no leſſe <hi>Wrath</hi> to break out from the Lord upon your ſelves and the Kingdome, than befell <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>all Judah,</hi> for<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.25.</note> 
               <hi>not rendring to the Lord according to</hi> a farre leſſe <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit done unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be divers other excellent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> of this comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but I muſt lay them all by, for haſte to the Laſt <hi>Point,</hi> which is this;</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</note>
               <hi>The Experience of Gods over-ruling and maſtering the rage of man in times paſt, is an undoubted aſſurance of the like for all to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Point, ſo clearely grounded on the Text which ſpeaks of future Deliverances built upon former mercies, and ſo ſtrongly bound downe with a confident <hi>aſſevera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the front, that <hi>ſurely</hi> it ſhall be even ſo, I ſhall paſſe over with a light foot.</p>
            <p>Nothing more common in Scripture than to conclude what God will ever doe, from what once he hath done. <hi>David,</hi> even in his youth, could be confident of this,<note n="n" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.37.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord that delivered me out of the paw of the Lyon, and out of the paw of the Beare, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistine.</hi> And afterwards, when that unnaturall Rebellion of <hi>Abſolom</hi> brake out ſo violently as made <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> too hot for <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.</note> cauſing him to flee <hi>whither he could by the way of the Wildernes;</hi> yet even then, after God upon his prayer had ſpoken comfort to him from expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of former deliverances, <hi>David</hi> growes ſo ſecure, that he that before durſt not ſtay in his owne houſe for danger, profeſſeth now to<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>lie downe and ſleep</hi> where he hath not an houſe wherein to put his head; and he that durſt not tarry in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with all the power he could rayſe againſt his ſonne, now profeſſeth in a wild howling deſolate Wildernes,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>I will not be afraid of ten thouſands of people that have ſet themſelves against mee round about.</hi> Thus, let God doe but any thing for him, and let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to live upon that while he lives. If God once <hi>lead him through green paſtures;</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.1.</note> his reſolution mounts high;<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Though I walk through the vally of the ſhadow of death, I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65693:28"/> will feare no evill;</hi> and, he ſoone arrives at this Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Surely, goodneſſe and mercy ſhall follow mee all the dayes of my life.</hi> Every mercy is an aſſurance of more. Nor was <hi>Paul</hi> behind <hi>David</hi> in this divine Art of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. If God raiſe him out of his bed from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous arreſt of a deſperate ſickneſſe, he rayſeth his faith higher than God rayſed his body; firſt, ſetting downe the mercy received,<note n="t" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver;</hi> then inferring hence, <hi>in whom we truſt that he will yet deliver.</hi> And at another time report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a gracious reſcue from the rage of <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>I was delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the mouth of the Lyon;</hi> he concludes thus, <hi>And the Lord ſhall deliver me from every evill work;</hi> that is, of evill men conſpiring againſt him before he ſhould have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his courſe.</p>
            <p>A truth ſo conſpicuous in the eyes of the faithfull, that they have pleaded this unto God himſelfe. <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he ſaw God in ſuch a rage, as to threaten the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> at once, falls to prayer, and pleads with God for a Pardon of courſe, becauſe he had given them many before.<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>Pardon, I beſeech thee the iniquitie of this people, according to the greatneſſe of thy mercy, and as thou haſt forgiven them from Aegypt even untill now.</hi> Never were the people nearer a dreadfull deſtruction, and yet this one Plea turned God quite about, and draws from him this anſwer,<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>Lo I have pardoned them according to thy word.</hi> So <hi>David,</hi> in a great danger, <hi>when the Philiſtines took him in Gath,</hi> uſeth the ſame Plea for deliverance;<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.13.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt delivered my ſoule from death, wilt not thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver my feet from falling?</hi> Which manner of ſpeaking plainly concludes, that it cannot be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Nay more. Not onely deliverances given to our ſelves, but to any others from the beginning of the world, is an undoubted argument to aſſure all the people of God of the like iſſue in all their ſtraits and diſtreſſes. When <hi>Iſaac</hi> was ſo ſtrangely delivered, beyond all exſpectation, the godly preſently made this uſe of it, and it grew to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, in all exigents;<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>God will be ſeen in the Mount.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:65693:29"/> When all things are ſo deſperate, that no help can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, yet the very delivering of <hi>Iſaac</hi> on the Mount of <hi>Moriah</hi> ſhall then aſſure them of a gracious deliverance. And it is Gods own plea to encourage <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to go on where <hi>Moſes</hi> left:<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>As I was with Moſes, ſo will I be with thee; I will never fail thee nor forſake thee.</hi> Which very Text the Apoſtle citeth as a Legacie bequeathed unto all Chriſtians, though not in being till many hundred yeers after <hi>Ioſhua</hi> was dead; to dehort them from covetouſnes, and to perſwade to contentation of minde by a firm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance upon God.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Let your converſation be without cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and be content with ſuch things as ye have: for God hath ſaid, I will never fail thee nor forſake thee; ſo that we may boldly ſay, The Lord is my helper, I will not fear what man ſhall do unto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> What was once, and but once ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to one <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> an extraordinarie perſon, called to an extraordinarie ſervice, wherein he was to encounter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie difficulties, is made by the Apoſtle as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Argument for all Gods people caſt upon any ſtrait, to claim the like to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> Nor will you ſtrange at it, if you conſider the grounds of it. For,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1 From the nature of God.</note>1. God is conſtant and unchangeable in all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, becauſe he is ſo in his nature. If his people alter not too much, he ſtill keeps one tenor.<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>I am Jehovah, I change not, therefore ye ſons of Iacob are not conſumed.</hi> His meaning is, that therefore they ſtill pertake of his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent mercies formerly ſhewed to <hi>Iacob</hi> their father, becauſe God is ſo unchangable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. From their conſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Covenant.</note>2. His people once in Covenant have alwayes the ſame intereſt in his wiſedome, power, providence, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo may ever plead that whereof they or any others have been at any time partakers. Hence the Church, long after <hi>David</hi> was gathered to his Fathers, thus expoſtulates with God;<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.49.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, where are thy former loving kindneſſes which thou ſwareſt unto David in truth.</hi> As if they ſhould ſay, be they not all ours by being in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> with thee, as <hi>David</hi> was?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65693:29"/>3. God never begins a work, but he goes through with it. <hi>When he begins he will alſo make an end,</hi> in perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercies, as well as in filling up plagues.<note place="margin">3. From Gods perfecting what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</note> It is a note of infamie upon a weak man to have it ſaid of him, <hi>This man began to build, and was not able to make an end.</hi> Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> knew what he did, when he pleaded for further mercy to Iſrael on this ground, that it would be ſaid by the enemy,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 9.28.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord was not able to bring him into the land which he promiſed them.</hi> Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo <hi>confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in this very thing, that he that hath begun a good work in his people, will alſo finiſh it unto the day of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then we ſee clear grounds why one deliverance aſſures many moe. Yet take this truth with this caution.<note place="margin">Yet obſerve a Caution.</note> Although God deliver his people all alike, <hi>effectivè,</hi> yet he doth not alwayes bind himſelf to give unto all his ſervants the ſame deliverance in <hi>ſpeciè,</hi> and in <hi>kind.</hi> But when he doth it not in <hi>kind,</hi> he doth it,</p>
            <p>Firſt, in <hi>equivalence:</hi> either the ſame,<note place="margin">1. Deliverance may be in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalence.</note> or another as good in it ſelf, and better for thee.<note n="f" place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly,</hi> for <hi>manner,</hi> and <hi>kind;</hi> as well as for the <hi>meanes.</hi> If life be beſt, he will preſerve thee alive. If death be better, even death ſhall be thy deliverance, and thy greater <hi>gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When God delivers not in <hi>kind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. If not in kind, yet ſuch as ſatisfieth.</note> yet that deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which he doth beſtow, gives full <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> and perfect <hi>content:</hi> ſo as other deliverance would not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted if it were tendred. Thoſe Primitive Saints that were expoſed to <hi>Martyrdome,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35.</note> 
               <hi>would not accept of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> (that is, of an eſcape with their lives) <hi>that they might obtain a better reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things obſerved, it ever holds good that, <hi>The experience of Gods ordering and over-ruling the rage of man in times paſt, is an undoubted aſſurance of the like for all time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this being ſo, I ſhall, in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> obſerve my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer method, beginning with a <hi>Parallell</hi> of this <hi>Truth</hi> and theſe Times: no truth being ſweeter than that whereof we have largeſt taſte and experience; nor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65693:30"/>
               <note place="margin">1. Uſe <hi>of the laſt</hi> Point.</note> than that which comes moſt home to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition.</p>
            <p>That great Deliverance we now celebrate, was not as a dead buſh to ſtop a preſent Gap onely,<note place="margin">1. Behold the experience of this upon our ſelves.</note> nor a mercy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring with that houre and occaſion; but, intended for a living, laſting, breeding Mercie that hath been very fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ever ſince. It was an in-let to further favours, and an earneſt of many moe bleſſings: for which, I appeal to Your own Experience who have duely obſerved Gods dealing with you. Many of You who have now the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſit Members of the High Court of Parliament were unborn, when the <hi>Powder Treaſon</hi> ſhould have been acted. Yet you cannot ſay, you were <hi>born out of due time:</hi> for that very Deliverance hath, ſince that, ſet down many a rich mercie at all your doores. This very <hi>Parliament</hi> ſpeaks out this truth to all the world.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Calling</hi> of it, and the <hi>ſitting</hi> of it, ſpeaks it. The many Conſpiracies that have been detected, the many Popiſh Deſignes that have been defeated, the many ſnares that have been broken, the many Mountains that have been levell'd, the mighty <hi>Nimrods</hi> that have been pluckt down, the unſupportable yokes of which our necks have been freed, thoſe <hi>whips of Scorpions</hi> the back-breaking heart-ſinking Courts which are now broken and diſſolved; the devouring ſword of war brandiſhed in the heart of this Kingdome, that is now put up; thoſe Rights and Liberties which had been led away captive paſt hope of reſcue, that are now reſtored; that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, neceſſarie, noble <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> for conſervation of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtation</hi> againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> into which both <hi>Houſes</hi> have worthily entred; that frequencie of <hi>Parliaments</hi> for preventing future inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of miſerie and bondage, that is now happily ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; this bleſſed opportunitie of ſitting in Parliament, at this time, for the more effectuall and timely quelling of that unhappie Rebellion of ſome <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and the providing for the continuance of this preſent Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, till all our grievances be heard and relieved, till
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65693:30"/> thoſe that are complained of as inſtruments of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction be brought forth to triall,<note place="margin">2. Uſe <hi>of the laſt</hi> Point.</note> till the Church be purged, Reformation perfected, and our Laws, eſtates, Liberties, and Religion be all ſetled and ſecured. Theſe, I ſay, and many moe do all ſpeak and proclaim the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, wonderfull, and invaluable mercies that have flowed in upon this unworthy and unthankfull Nation from that admirable defeat of the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107, 2.</note> 
               <hi>let the redeemed of the Lord, whom he hath redeemed from the hand of the enemie,</hi> ſay, <hi>that his mercie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for ever.</hi> Yea, let all that fear him, ſay,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.19.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord who daily loadeth us with his benefits, even the God of our ſalvation;</hi> and let them put a <hi>Selah</hi> to it,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.18.</note> 
               <hi>for the generation to come, that the people which are yet unborn may praiſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> 2. But, what terror and torment ſpeaks this to all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, whether Papiſts, or Atheiſts, that ſpeak,<note place="margin">Terror to the wicked.</note> and do ſo exceeding proudly from day to day, as if all were theirs, and that nothing could hinder the ſatisfying of their luſt upon the Goſpel! What ſtone have they left unturned? what plot unattempted? And yet, what Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the many which they have contrived, hath taken effect? Will they not ſee that, in all their <hi>rage</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, they do<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>imagine</hi> but <hi>a vain thing?</hi> that they are ſure of a <hi>hard</hi> bargain of it (like that of a naked bodie)<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>to kick againſt the pricks?</hi> that it is a deſperate ſervice they daily go upon? Have they not miſcarried, and gone by the worſe all along? and may they not, out of their miſcarriages paſt, as out of an <hi>Experimentall Prognoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> read their deſtiny for all time to come?</p>
            <p>Do they not know that God hath engaged himſelf to his people, that<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.17.</note> 
               <hi>no weapon that is formed againſt them ſhall proſper?</hi> Even <hi>Hamans</hi> wife (though a heathen) could tell her husband enraged againſt <hi>Mordecai,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>If Mordecai be of the ſeed of the Jews, before whom thou haſt begun to fall, thou ſhalt not prevail againſt him, but ſhalt ſurely fall before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know God ſometimes in anger, gives his people into
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65693:31"/> the hands of their enemies, to chaſtiſe and humble them. But, mark the iſſue: the tail of the ſtorme ever lights up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>the rods of his anger.</hi> For, the Lord hath ſaid it,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>Yet a little while, and the indignation</hi> (againſt the godly) <hi>ſhall ceaſe: and mine anger, in their deſtruction:</hi> that is, of thoſe whom he imployed to correct them. Yea, which is a deeper cut to a malicious heart, God doth, at laſt, uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring his enemies to confuſion even by thoſe poore, deſpiſed, oppreſſed out-caſts of Iſrael, whom the wicked in their rage had reſolved to devoure.<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will make Ieruſalem a cup of trembling,</hi> (or <hi>of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) unto all people round about, when they ſhall be in the ſiege both againſt Iudah and Ieruſalem. And in that day will I make Ieruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m a burdenſome ſtone for all people: all that burden themſelves with it:</hi> that is, labour <hi>to take it up and throw it out, ſhall be cut in pieces, though all the people of the earth be gathered together againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that wicked men would yet deſiſt from their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt the godly, before the <hi>Lords wrath be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, and they periſh</hi> for ever! But, if they will not <hi>be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed,</hi> I muſt leave with them that which the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to the uncureable enemies of his Church here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore;<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.9, 10</note> 
               <hi>Gird your ſelves, and ye ſhall be broken in pieces; yea, gird your ſelves and ye ſhall be broken in pieces. Take counſell together and it ſhall come to nought, ſpeak the word and it ſhall not ſtand, for God is with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> 3. But O the fathomleſſe conſolation and ſteeling en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement that this Truth adminiſtreth to all the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;<note place="margin">Comfort to the godly.</note> but more eſpecially to You who are now imployed by God and the King in the great ſervice of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome! Is it ſo that <hi>your ſouls be among Lions,</hi> and that <hi>you lie among thoſe that are ſet on fire,</hi> to plot Treaſons againſt You continually, and boldly to breathe out bloody threatnings, ſo that when you go forth in the morning, you can ſcarce hope to return in the evening in peace? Do but caſt up your accounts and experiments of Gods former Mercies in protecting, directing, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and delivering of You hitherto, and you need no
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65693:31"/> other <hi>Prognoſtication</hi> to foretell what will befall you;<note place="margin">3. Uſe <hi>of the laſt</hi> Point.</note> nor better aſſurance that God will go on and preſerve and cover you, to direct and proſper You (while you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on him, and walk with him) maugre all the rage, and power, malice, and ſubtiltie of all men and devils all together againſt you.</p>
            <p>Nay could it be imagined that you never had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods power and goodneſſe in any extraordinary preſervations and deliverances of your ſelves at all: yet, if you do but look abroad upon the many mercies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on others, in any age of the world; yea, if you look but upon this very Deliverance given to your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours, this will be enough to aſſure you of like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and preſervation for ever. For every one of Gods ſervants are entitled to all the mercies and glorious works that ever the Lord wrought for any of his people from the beginning of the world. If you doubt hereof, remember what you have already heard from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who hath put it out of queſtion, in the place before cited, where he voucheth that particular encouragement given to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> as an undubitable promiſe to all the godly;<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>I will never fail thee nor forſake thee: ſo that we may boldly ſay, the Lord is my help, I will not fear what man ſhall do unto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Be therefore exhorted hence, 1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The laſt</hi> Uſe. Exhortation.</note> to make this uſe of all former mercies. 2. To labour to be capable of this experiment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Make this uſe of all former mercies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Make this Vſe of former mercies.</note> Look on what we finde acted, or written of Gods goodneſſe to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not as bare hiſtories of things done, but as Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks and aſſurances of the like again; as upon <hi>Book-caſes</hi> adjudged, that may be vouched unto God as Preſidents in this time of trouble and danger. It is the great fault of too many, when they read in Scripture of wonderfull protections and deliverances, they behold them onely to admire the acts done, but not to rowle themſelves, by vertue thereof, upon God, for the like. Howbeit, the Apoſtle tels us,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever was written afore-time, was
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65693:32"/> written for our learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The laſt <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that we through patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Scriptures might have hope:</hi> of what, but of this; that, as others before us have been graciouſly born upon wings of mercie; even ſo we alſo ſhall, with no leſſe power and tenderneſſe, be carried through all ſtormes and dangers that may ſet upon us in any ſervice or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for God, beyond all humane helps or hopes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Labour to be capable of like mercies.</note>2. Labour to be capeable of further mercies by vertue of thoſe alreadie conferred. Although God be gratiouſly indulgent, yet is he not inconſiderately prodigall of mercies to all that ſcrape acquaintance with him in their troubles. There are ſome to whom God, after many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, ſaith peremptorily,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.13</note> 
               <hi>I will deliver you no more:</hi> It concerns all, therefore, to make this ſure that they be ſuch who may exſpect further deliverances from the God of their ſalvation. To this purpoſe, three things muſt be done: You muſt <hi>beleeve</hi> in him, <hi>walk</hi> with him, and <hi>ſtand</hi> for him.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. Beleeve in him.</note>1. <hi>Beleeve in him.</hi> When <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> and his people, fearing to be ſwallowed up of an huge hoſt that came out againſt them, were by a Prophet aſſured of victory with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtriking a blow, <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> preſently inculcates this upon his ſubjects,<note n="o" place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.20.</note> 
               <hi>Beleeve in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall ye be eſtabliſhed, beleeve his Prophets, ſo ſhall ye proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faith makes a man even omnipotent.<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.23.</note> 
               <hi>All things are poſſible to him that beleeveth.</hi> It<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.13.</note> binds Gods hands when he would deſtroy. It commands his help when his people are in diſtreſſe;<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.11.</note> 
               <hi>Concerning the work of my hands command ye me.</hi> On the other hand, Infidelity doth weaken Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie it ſelf, in regard of the effects that otherwiſe would be produced. It makes him<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.8.</note> 
               <hi>as a ſtrong man that cannot ſave.</hi> When Chriſt did ſo many mighty works in the dayes of his fleſh, no man felt the effect, but ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved.<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.29.</note> 
               <hi>According to your faith be it unto you,</hi> ſaid he to the blind men that came to be healed. So it fell out to thoſe of his own countrey;<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>he could there do no mighty worke, ſave that he laid his hands upon a few ſick folks and healed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65693:32"/> them:</hi> the reaſon is couched in the next words, <hi>he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled at their unbelief.</hi> Which ſhews plainly, that let Gods power be what it will, our neceſſities as great as can be, and his promiſes never ſo firm and punctuall for you, yet,<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>if you will not beleeve, ſurely ye ſhall not be eſtabliſhed.</hi> Therefore <hi>beleeve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Walk with God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Walk with God.</note> This was required of <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull, when God promiſed to do ſo much for him and his ſeed,<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>Walk before me and be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</hi> When<note n="y" place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Iehoſhaphat walked in the first wayes of his father David,</hi> the <hi>Lord was with him, and ſtrengthened the kingdome in his hand.</hi> And<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>the fear of the Lord fell upon all the kingdomes round about Iudah, ſo that they made no warre against Iehoſhaphat.</hi> Yea, the moſt inveterate ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Judah, the <hi>Philiſtines, brought him gifts and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents.</hi> Thus God makes his ſervants that walk with him ſo ſure of protection, that they become a terror to thoſe that would be a terror to them.</p>
            <p>He that walks with God is ſure to fare as God himſelf doth. Fellow travellers uſe to communicate each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch things as they have, if any of the company fall into diſtreſſe: ſo the Lord communicates all his power, wiſedome, and goodneſſe to all that walk with him, as they ſtand in need of any, or of all of theſe.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord God is a ſunne and a ſhield, and no good thing will he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from them that walk uprightly.</hi> Yea,<note n="a" place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.9.</note> his <hi>eyes run too and fro, throughout the whole earth, to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in behalf of them whoſe heart is perfect towards him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Stand for him,</hi> and he will ſtand for you.<note place="margin">3. Stand for God.</note> Be zealous for God, and he will put on zeal as a cloak for you. If you will <hi>help the Lord againſt the mighty,</hi> eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe proud enemies that tread down his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or imbaſe them with alloyes of their own, you ſhall ſoon finde him ſpeaking to you in your ſtraits and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 18.3.</note> 
               <hi>I am as thou art, and my people as thy people, and we will be with thee in the warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:65693:33"/>
            <p>Give me leave, I beſeech You, to ſpeak freely to You; I will doe it humbly too. At Your firſt ſitting downe, You expreſſed many brave and noble reſolutions, of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gods buſineſſe the precedency of all other Your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: and Your beginnings promiſed much. Howbeit, I know not how it comes to paſſe, but ſo it is, that Gods Work lies yet undone. Matters of Religion lie a bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; all Government and Diſcipline of the Church is laid in her Grave, and all putredinous vermine of bold Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and frantick Sectaries glory in her aſhes; making her fall their own riſing to mount our Pulpits, to offer ſtrange fire, to expell the graveſt, ableſt, and moſt eminent Miniſters in the Kingdome, (if not out of their Pulpits, yet) out of the hearts of their people as a company of weak men, formaliſts, time-ſervers, no Miniſters of Chriſt, but Limbs of Antichriſt, having no calling except from the Devill; and to forſake our Aſſemblies as Babyloniſh and Antichriſtian, ſo as in ſhort time they will not leave us the face of a Church. And yet, no courſe is taken to ſuppreſſe their fury, and to reduce them to order, which (as things now ſtand) will never be, till You put your hands to the Cure. I know your buſineſſes and diverſions have been extraordinary: yet in the midſt of them all, You have found opportunitie to vindicate and ſetle your own Rights and Liberties. Therefore I hope You will finde both time and hearts to conſider what is to be done for that God who hath done ſo much for You beyond all exſpectation.</p>
            <p>Farre be it from any among You to ſay, <hi>it is not yet a time.</hi> Remember how unkindly God took the neglect of his <hi>Houſe</hi> by the <hi>Jewes</hi> whom he had reſtored from <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie,</hi> albeit they forgat not the daily <hi>Sacrifice</hi> in the due place, and were oppoſed by many potent enemies, (the Kings <hi>Great Officers</hi> in <hi>Judeah</hi>) who procured from <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus</hi> a<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Decree</hi> to ſtay the building of the <hi>Lords Houſe;</hi> which cauſed a ceſſation of forty-one yeares, even<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>untill the ſecond of Darius Nothus.</hi> In this caſe, much might have been ſaid for laying aſide the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65693:33"/> Work; yet becauſe the chiefe of the people did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſolicite the Perſian Monarchs to reverſe that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that the building might goe on; but, followed their own buſines cloſe, built their own houſes and ſeiled them ſumptuouſly, ſowed their fields, and omitted nothing for their own Eſtates and Liberties, God did continually blow upon all, and curſed every bleſſing.</p>
            <p>When they marvailed at the matter, He bad <hi>Haggai</hi> the Prophet to tell them the reaſon, and to perſwade them to reflect upon their own wayes, as the onely cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>This people ſay, the time is not come, the time that the Lords Houſe ſhould be built.</hi> To this the Lord makes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Is it time for You, O yee, to dwell in your ſeiled hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and this Houſe lie waſt?</hi> Can you finde time for your ſelves, and none for Mee? Should I bleſſe you in purſuit of your own affaires whiles you neglect mine? Nay, <hi>Conſider your wayes.</hi> See what you have gotten, in the iſſue, by all the Labour you have taken for your ſelves, while you have done nothing to ſet forward the Houſe of your God. Yee have ſowne <hi>much and bring in little, yee eate but you have not enough, yee drinke but yee are not filled, &amp;c.</hi> Thus it was with them, although an Edict was ſtill in force againſt building of the <hi>Temple;</hi> becauſe they did not cordially doe their utmoſt, to obtaine the repeale of that Ordinance, but rather made uſe of it to purſue their own buſineſſe with more zeale and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</p>
            <p>And hath not the ſame God begun the ſame courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, at this very time? <hi>Conſider your wayes.</hi> When they who ſolicited the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> humbly prayed that the <hi>matters of Religion</hi> might be put to ſome iſſue; the <hi>disbanding of the Armies,</hi> was thought more neceſſary, to put an end to that charge. When that was done, what followed? Was any thing done for God? Surely, You can beſt tell. And what have wee gotten? In ſtead of the former <hi>Armies,</hi> God hath now laid upon You a buſineſſe of more difficultie, and likely to prove more coſtly and bloudy, by kindling a fire in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the unſpeakable
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65693:34"/> perſecutions, and butcheries of the poore <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there; and, when thoſe flames will be quenched, or how far they may extend, is known only to Him whoſe Cauſe (I feare) is not ſufficiently taken to heart? But this be ſure of, it will never be better; but, more and more occaſion of exhauſting your Eſtates (which You have ſpent ſo much time to ſecure) will be ſtill adminiſtred, ſo long as You ſhall deferre <hi>the building of the Lords Houſe,</hi> I meane, the ſetling and ſecuring of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> This is that <hi>unum neceſſarium</hi> which (what ever ſome think) will undoubtedly ſave all: and, without which, all will be loſt at home, as well as abroad.</p>
            <p>O therefore let mee be bold in the Name of the Lord (whoſe Servant I am, and whoſe Cauſe I now plead,) to give You the ſame Counſell that God by his ſervant <hi>Haggai,</hi> gave to the <hi>Jewes</hi> who ſeemed to approve the Work, but pretended many Lyons to be in the way.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Goe up to the Mountaine, and bring wood, and build the Houſe, and I will take pleaſure in it, and I will be glorified, ſaith the Lord.</hi> What ever your own thoughts be, lay them aſide to conſider ſeriouſly what God exſpects from You. Try that Courſe, and ſee what a bleſſing will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; how ſoone, how ſtrangely God will turne all things about, remove all difficulties, and work wonderfully for You and our poore Brethren in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is no Empiricall <hi>Doſis,</hi> but a <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi> For mark the iſſue of taking this Counſell, in the <hi>Jewes</hi> Caſe. Such as <hi>beleeved the Prophet,</hi> and <hi>feared the Lord,</hi> laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the hot purſuit of their own affaires, and did as they were commanded. They ſet upon the <hi>building</hi> of the <hi>Lords Houſe.</hi> And the next newſe was;<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Then ſpake Haggai the Lords Meſſenger, the Lords meſſage unto the people; I am with you, ſaith the Lord.</hi> That is, now they ſhould find him <hi>with them</hi> to purpoſe: firſt, in carrying up the <hi>building,</hi> which (beſide the ſeverall pauſes and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Work) had been forty-two yeares,<note place="margin">That Houſe was forty-ſix years in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.20.</note> at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times, laboured in, and yet not finiſhed; and had then lain forty-one yeares together, without ſo much as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65693:34"/> a ſtone laid in it. Now, it ſhould goe up ſo faſt, that one foure yeares more ſhould perfect the work. For, they<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>finiſhed it in the ſixth</hi> yeare of <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi> having ſet upon it in<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.15.</note> the ſecond of his Reigne, as before is ſhewed.</p>
            <p>Nor did God thus proſper them in his own Work on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but bleſſed them in all things elſe they took in hand for themſelves. And whereas before, there was nothing but ſidings and factions; ſome<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.10. &amp;c. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18,</note> complying with the Great Officers of the Perſian and Mediſh Emperours that then ruled over them, others oppoſing, and all thwarting one another, and thriving in nothing; afterwards, God did on the ſudden turne the ſtreame, knit them together<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.</note> in a <hi>Covenant with God,</hi> and thereby<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 10.28, 29.</note> unitd them alſo one to another; ſo as, not onely a new face, but a new ſtate of things preſently appeared; and God was as good as his word, not onely in <hi>taking pleaſure in his houſe,</hi> but in thoſe that <hi>built</hi> it; For, ſo himſelfe tells them;<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>From this day will I bleſſe you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a memorable Inſtance; and I would to God You would preſident your ſelves, by it, which till You doe, I ſhall never exſpect good of any of your <hi>Labours,</hi> or <hi>Lawes</hi> already made for your ſelves: Nor ſhall You ſatisfie the expectations of thoſe that ſent You hither, and put ſo great a Truſt into your hands. Even men who at other times care no more than <hi>Gallio</hi> for matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; now that they ſee all mens ſpirits to be up for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they alſo are (in their wayes) zealous to have ſomewhat done in it, and for it, as well as others.</p>
            <p>I beſeech You therefore in the Name of that Great God, whom You ſerve, and who hath hitherto bleſt You, and for the peace and proſperitie of this Church and Kingdome, to reſume and purſue your firſt thoughts of ſetting up <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> as becomes You in a Regular way, which I have ever taken to be, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to your aſſiſtance a <hi>free Synode</hi> of Grave <hi>Miniſters</hi> of this <hi>Nation.</hi> Not that I take upon me to preſcribe any thing, but humbly to offer it to conſideration onely, that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65693:35"/> ſo among the ſeverall wayes and meanes propounded, Your Wiſedomes may ſelect and proſecute what You ſhall finde to be the ſureſt and moſt honorable way to cure the Ulcers of the Time, that daily feſter more and more: That our Church and the Government thereof may be no longer laid waſte, and expoſed to Confuſion, under the plauſible pretence of <hi>not forcing mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</hi> To put all men into a courſe of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> in Gods way, is not to <hi>force the Conſcience;</hi> but, to ſet up God in his due place, and to bring all his people into the paths of righteouſneſſe and life.</p>
            <p>You ſee how God hath unexpectedly put you into fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſity of more ſupplies from the people, for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all that foment or countenance ſuch a prodigious Conſpiracie. And you cannot be ignorant of the generall diſcontent at this, that there is yet no more done for <hi>Religion,</hi> by reforming what is amiſſe, and by ſetling what ſhould be ſo reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Would you therefore once go roundly to work in this Great Enterpriſe, and make the people to ſee and be aſſured of what I know you intend, namely, the further <hi>Reformation</hi> of the many things out of order in our <hi>Church and Diſcipline,</hi> and the perfecting of that which hath ſo many yeers lain unpoliſhed, You might ſoon command the hearts, and purſes, and lives of all good Chriſtians in the publique ſervice of the King and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, without regreet, or gain-ſaying; and be able to do more in a ſhort time, than otherwiſe you ſhall ever effect while you live.</p>
            <p>Look upon <hi>David.</hi> When this was once ſeriouſly and ſincerely ſetled in his heart, to <hi>build God an Houſe,</hi> God took it ſo kindly, that though he reſolved to reſerve that Work for <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.</note> yet he ſent a meſſage to <hi>David,</hi> that he would <hi>build him an houſe,</hi> and eſtabliſh both his <hi>houſe</hi> and <hi>kingdome</hi> upon him. And not onely ſo; but, when ſo ever <hi>David</hi> had need of extraordinarie help, God never failed to go out with him whither ſoever he went. And it is very remarkable, that moſt of the Great Victories
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65693:35"/> which <hi>David</hi> atchieved, fell to him after his <hi>reſolution</hi> of building the <hi>Temple.</hi> For the Text ſaith it expreſly, that,<note n="l" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>After theſe things, David</hi> ſmote the <hi>Philistines;</hi> and after that, the <hi>Moabites;</hi> then, <hi>Hadadazer;</hi> and then, the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and others, none being able to ſtand before him.</p>
            <p>And thus would it be with you, when, in zeal for God, you follow his ſteps. What ever the difficulties and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements be, when <hi>Zorobabel</hi> fals cloſe to work, what <hi>mountain,</hi> ſo <hi>great</hi> and high, that ſhall not <hi>become a plain?</hi> No plots, no power of hell ſhould prevail againſt you. Do you carry on Gods work, he will be ſure to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie on yours, and make you the honour and ſtrength of the King and Kingdome in all the Kings Noble deſignes for the good of his Subjects. Thoſe unnaturall Rebels that now <hi>rage</hi> ſo deſperately, ſhould be <hi>but bread for you;</hi> and all your enemies ſhould be compelled to lick the duſt of your feet. I ſhall therefore cloſe all with that of the ſame <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſonne, touching the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Temple,<note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 22.16.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſe, and be doing, and the Lord be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped in ſome Copies, correct thus. <hi>The firſt number ſhews the</hi> page; <hi>the ſecond, the</hi> line.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. li. 20. <hi>dele</hi> and. li. 29. r. (2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 14.) 2. 2. <hi>dele</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>and.</hi> 4. 9. r. <hi>not.</hi> 6. 2. r. <hi>of clay.</hi> 7. 15. r. <hi>a little.</hi> li. 18. r. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>math.</hi> and in marg. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 17. 17. r. <hi>our Cities.</hi> 20. 2. r. <hi>Cunning.</hi> 21. 14. r. for. 24. in marg. r. <hi>Haſſenmuller.</hi> 34. 23. <hi>dele</hi> the 36. 19. <hi>dele</hi> not. 49. 1. r. <hi>within.</hi> and li. 6. r. <hi>which makes.</hi> pag. 53. 8. r. them. 55. 20. r. Godly.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
